<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_1055">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>London, The Khalili Collections, KFQ 78</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="48">The Khalili Collections
                            , London</repository>
            <idno>KFQ 78</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
              <p>Cf. entry by François Déroche about fragment KFQ 78 (Déroche, <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/QJQEKNSJ" sameAs="QJQEKNSJ" type="zotero">The Abbasid Tradition, London 1992</ref>, p. 123): "67 / Single folio / 9th century AD / 11.2x20.3cm / <hi rend="italic">Material</hi> Parchment / <hi rend="italic">Accession no</hi>. KFQ78 / <hi rend="italic">Published</hi> Sotheby’s, London, 14 December 1987, lot no. 149 / The folio bears no text, for both sides are occupied by a panel of illumination characteristic of the Abbasid period. In contrast to cat.75, where the central field occupies a smaller proportion of the design as a whole, the development of the central pattern is here given more prominence. On one side, the illumination (6.8x14.4cm) is surrounded by a frame in which an undulating gold scroll is set against a red ground. The central field (5x12.6cm) is filled with a trellis pattern drawn in ink. The trellis is formed by double fillets, and the points where they cross are filled with brown ink. Each lozenge formed by the trellis contains a stylized plant-based motif in the form of an elongated trefoil reserved against a hatched ground. Occasionally, there are two half-leaves above the trefoil. / The illumination on the reverse is almost identical in size (6.9x14.6cm) but relies on a totally different composition. A slightly thinner undulating gold scroll on a red ground forms the frame, but the field (5.6x13.1cm) is illuminated in a more complex fashion. Geometric elements defined by bands reserved between two gold fillets combine to form a pattern of interlace. Three circles are set side by side within a rectangle whose corners describe a small loop, and they are all linked by two interlocking bands of semicircular loops to form oblong cartouches contiguous with the frame and various cruciform patterns in the centre. The three largest, which are contained within the circles, are ornamented with a plant-based motif. / Despite great skill, the illuminator has not been able to create a design that is symmetrical on the vertical axis. The central composition is not complete, as two elements have been left out, and the complex loop does not intersect in the middle of the side adjacent to the inner margin. As often happens, the illumination is not set symmetrically in the centre of the page: the upper and lower margins differ in size. / On both pages, there is a large vignette filled with palmette motifs in the left-hand margin.”</p>
            </summary>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <extent>Folios: 1
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>203</width><height>112</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="0">0 - 0 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate>800-900</origDate>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>assistance: Yunus C. Öç</p>
                <p>metadata: Michael Marx</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>(No content available)</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
