<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_1439">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>London, The Khalili Collections, QUR 430</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
        <availability xml:id="imageRights-1" status="restricted" default="false">
          <p>Image credits: Déroche (1992) - The Abbasid Tradition.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="48">The Khalili Collections
                            , London</repository>
            <idno>QUR 430</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
              <p>166 fol. on parchment; Shelfmark: QUR 430; 30 lines per page; Dimensions: 73 x 60 mm; Script style: New Style; Estimated date of production: 950-1000.</p>
              <p> </p>
              <p>The catalogue written by François Déroche gives the following information (<ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/QJQEKNSJ" sameAs="QJQEKNSJ" type="zotero">Déroche, The Abbasid Tradition, London 1992</ref>, p. 153): "82 / Single-volume Qur'an / Second half of the 10th century AD / 166 folios, 7.3 x 6cm, with 30 lines to the page / <hi rend="italic">Material</hi> Parchment / <hi rend="italic">Text area</hi> 5.4 x 4.1cm / <hi rend="italic">Script</hi> A miniature form of NS <hi rend="italic">Binding</hi> Later lacquer covers with floral decoration and a black leather spine / <hi rend="italic">Accession no.</hi> QUR 430 / <hi rend="italic">Published</hi> Christie's, London, 11 April 1989, lot no. 52 / Although there are considerable differences in their physical construction and illumination, cat. 82 and the two quires from Palermo discussed above (cat. 81) are closely related in terms of their script. The proportions of the two hands are quite different, and this obscures their similarities. Indeed, the script of cat. 82 is so small that some details that are clearly apparent in the larger hand of cat. 81 could not be retained. Nevertheless, the letter forms are basically the same. / The existence of similar letter forms in the two manuscripts does not mean that they were both produced in Sicily. They are very different from a codicological point of view, in terms both of their format and of the construction of their quires: those of cat.82 have eight leaves and are almost exclusively made of bifolios arranged in groups of four, while cat. 81 is more conservative and has quires of ten folios. / On folio 1b-2a, the number of surahs, verses, words etc. has been written in gold D.V script (7 lines to the page) within a strapwork frame. The illumination on the following double page (folio 2b-3a) is organized around a central circular design and follows a model used in vertical-format Qur'ans throughout the 10th to 12th centuries AD. The composition is outlined by a white band which surrounds the field (4.3 x 2.9 cm) and defines the central circle (diameter 1.5cm). The circle is filled with a gold chessboard pattern in which the black squares suggest the form of lozenges and is surrounded by a row of gold dots. In each corner the white band creates a quarter-circle filled with minute gold trefoils on what was probably a black ground. A gold and black chessboard pattern, with squares larger than in the central circle and set at an oblique angle, fills the four areas between the central circular figure and the corner-pieces. The frame (0.5 cm wide) echoes the strapwork motif of folios 1b- 2a. A medial vignette extends into the margin on both pages, and the whole composition is outlined in blue. On folio 3b, the titles of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-fātiḥah </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-baqarah</hi> appear in D.V script reserved against the gold ground of a decorative band. / The title and verse count of the other surahs are written in gold D script and outlined in black ink. To the side of the surah heading, a vignette extends into the outer margin. All the vignettes are outlined in blue, but their shapes vary greatly. The components are all drawn from the plant world, except in nine cases with short inscriptions (see folios 37b, 71b, 75b, 114b, 140b, 144a, 151b, 153a and 158b). Trimming of the pages has made these inscriptions illegible. In the margin, under the vignette, the place of revelation was recorded in gold D script. In one place, below the vignette next to the heading of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat</hi> <hi rend="italic">al-zumar</hi> (XXXIX) on folio 125b, this inscription is contained in a square outlined in ink. / The text, which is defective at the end, is written in black ink, without diacritical dots. Red dots indicate the vocalization. A 3.1.2 rosette has been placed in the text to mark the end of every tenth verse. It is accompanied in the margin by a 4.A.II device, which contains the number of verses written out in a gold script, perhaps a type of style D, on a green or red ground. The margins have been trimmed so severely that the markers that recorded the conventional divisions of the Qur'anic text (<hi rend="italic">juzʾ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ḥizb</hi>, <hi rend="italic">subʿ </hi>etc.) have almost disappeared. A gold frame outlined in black surrounds the text at the beginning of the manuscript (folios 3b-9b ); it may be a later addition. / On folio 1b, there is an impression of the seal of Qiwam al-Din Muhammad al-Husayni, which is dated AH 1072 (AD 1661-2); folio 2b bears an impression of the seal of Crown Prince Muhammad Hasan Mirza, pretender to the Qajar throne."</p>
              <p> </p>
              <p>Unfortunately only a small selection of images from this manuscripts (as in the catalogue <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/QJQEKNSJ">Abbasid Tradition</ref>, p. 152) are on display in this catalogue.</p>
            </summary>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_706949" n="3v">
              <title type="numeric" key="001:000:000-002:010:011">
                                    001:000:000-002:010:011
                                </title>
            </msItem>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_706950" n="4r">
              <title type="numeric" key="002:010:012-002:025:013">
                                    002:010:012-002:025:013
                                </title>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <extent>Folios: 166
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>60</width><height>73</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="30">30 - 30 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                new style
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate>950-1000</origDate>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>assistance: Yunus C. Öç</p>
                <p>metadata: Michael Marx</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <surface n="3v" xml:id="mysql_id_76514">
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1439/ab84219c-aa27-4df0-b1bd-f84a78df1945/manuscript-1439-page-76514-image-68626.png"/>
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1439/322dae21-8270-42b9-88a3-a5b334e56df9/manuscript-1439-page-76514-image-68627.png"/>
    </surface>
    <surface n="4r" xml:id="mysql_id_76515">
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1439/d7151a43-1386-4037-aa20-5dbd5aefeec7/manuscript-1439-page-76515-image-68628.png"/>
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1439/399cc39d-1ecc-4bf6-a068-452980b29ef6/manuscript-1439-page-76515-image-68629.png"/>
    </surface>
  </facsimile>
</TEI>
