<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_1045">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>London, The Khalili Collections, QUR 306</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="48">The Khalili Collections
                            , London</repository>
            <idno>QUR 306</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
              <p>69 fol.; Writing surface: parchment; Shelfmark: QUR 306; Lines per page: 5; Dimensions: 62 x 93 mm; Qurʾānic Text: Q 27:56-Q 28:2, Q 28:4-32, Q 28:36-81, Q 28:84-Q 29:41; Script style: kūfī D.Vc; Estimated date of production: 800-1000.</p>
              <p>Cf. entry by François Déroche about fragment QUR 306 (Déroche, <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/QJQEKNSJ">The Abbasid Tradition, London 1992</ref>, p. 112): "59 / Part 20 of a 30-part Qur‘an / 10th century AD / 69 folios, 6.2x9.3cm, with 5 lines to the page / <hi rend="italic">Material</hi> Parchment / <hi rend="italic">Text area</hi> 2.7x6cm / <hi rend="italic">Script</hi> Close to style D.Vc / <hi rend="italic">Binding</hi> Probably 16th century / <hi rend="italic">Accession no</hi>. QUR306 / The script is related to D.Vc, but some letter forms appear in more than one guise: independent <hi rend="italic">alif</hi>, for example, either has the form characteristics of group D, with its crescent-shaped lower hook, or that of group E, a simple vertical stroke. The same holds true for <hi rend="italic">nūn</hi>, whose shape varies so much that it is difficult to define. The shape of final <hi rend="italic">mīm</hi>, on the other hand, is fairly constant: with its straight vertical tail, it conforms to one of the two types usually found in D.Vc manuscripts. (The alternative has sinuous tail.) As one might expect in a style related to group D, the shafts of <hi rend="italic">kāf</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ṭāʾ</hi> are sometimes curved. / The surviving text consists of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-naml</hi> (XXVII), verse 56, to <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-qaṣaṣ</hi> (XXVIII), verse 2 (folios 1-14); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-qaṣaṣ</hi>, verses 4-32 (folios 15-28) and 36-81 (folios 29-49); and <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-qaṣaṣ</hi>, verse 84, to <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-ʿankabūt</hi> (XXIX), verse 41 (folios 50-68). It is written in black ink. The diacriticals are a later addition. The vocalization is indicated by red dots. The verses are not punctuated, but the end of every tenth verse is marked by a 3.A.II device, with the number of verses written out in gold at its centre. The title and verse count of the surah are written in gold letters outlined in ink and are accompanied in the margin by a vignette. / Restoration has altered the appearance of the manuscript to some extent. A frame has been drawn around the text, and catchwords in a cursive hand have been added. The loss of some folios left the text incomplete, and the lacunae were filled by writing the missing parts of the text in the margins of the folios facing the lost leaves. Quires of eight folios seem to have been the rule, but it was not always possible to examine their composition because some seem to have been trimmed along the inner side when the binding was restored. / This section has an illuminated frontispiece and finispiece. Both of these were probably double-page compositions, but only one half of each survives. They share the same pattern. The field (folio 1a, 3x6cm; folio 69a, 3.1x6.4cm) is divided into three rectangles surrounded by a band of gold dots. The central compartment, which is slightly larger than the other two, contains a cruciform interlace motif made up of white fillets, the rest of the space being occupied by gold dots or leaf designs. In the two lateral compartments, a single arabesque element, white on a blue and red ground, is oriented towards the outer margin. / The later covers are of black leather. Gold fillets have been painted along the edges, and a central medallion has been stamped and gilded. The spine has been remade, and there is no flap. The doublures are of red leather and also have gold fillets painted along the edges. The central mandorla and its extensions are in filigree work on a blue ground.”</p>
            </summary>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <extent>Folios: 69
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>93</width><height>62</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="5">5 - 5 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                kūfī D.Vc
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate>800-1000</origDate>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>metadata: Michael Marx</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>(No content available)</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
