<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_2248">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Istanbul, Topkapı Palace Museum (Topkapı Sarayı Müzesi), E. H. 2 [= Karatay 25]</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="7">Topkapı Palace Museum (Topkapı Sarayı Müzesi)
                            , Istanbul</repository>
            <idno>E. H. 2 [= Karatay 25]</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
              <p>414 fol.; Writing surface: parchment; Shelfmark: E. H. 2; Text: Complete Qur'an (?); 16 lines per page; Dimensions: 272 x 195 mm; Script style: kūfī; Estimated date of production: 2nd (8th) to 3rd (9th) centuries [according to Karatay]. </p>
              <p>This entry is based on the catalogue of Fehmi E. Karatay (1888-1968). Currently we do not have access to the images. With exceptions, the catalogue does not contain precise information on the distribution of the text throughout the pages. For this reason, only fol. 1 is given. </p>
              <p><ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/UEN2FUP7" sameAs="UEN2FUP7" type="zotero">Karatay (1962)</ref> describes the manuscripts as follows, p. 9: "25 E. H. 2 Aynı Parşömen. 195mm boy ve 272mm eninde 414 yaprak. Sahifede harekeleri kırmızı noktalarla ve noktaları yeşille konmuş kûfî yazı ile 200mm uzunl.[uğunda] 16 satır. Bu mushaf da Hz. ʿAlī b. abī Ṭālib’e izafe ediliyor ise de II-III. asır işi olması daha kuvvetle muhtemeldir. Y. 412 den sonrası 307 cumad el-ulasında (919) ʿAbd Allāh b. Muḥammad el-Ḥazracī tarafından Hizānameul-maʿmūrat az-Zaynīya en Nāblūsiye için eksik yaprakların tamamlandığı zikredilmektedir. Y. 1b, 2a, 2b, 3a da Arap üslûbunda hendesî tezinatı havi dört müzehhep levha, ve Y. 3b, 4a da Fatiḥa ve Baḳara surelerinin baş tarafı altın ile yazılmış ve kenarlarda Arap üslûbunda tezhibat vardır. Kenarlarının bazı yerleri kâğıtla tamir edilmiştir. Cildi miklep ve şemseli koyu kahve rengi Osmanlı eseridir."</p>
              <p>This can be translated as follows: "25 E. H. 2 Same Parchment. 414 leaves of 195 mm height and 272 mm width. The text area written in Kufic script with red vowel marks and green consonant pointings [contains] 16 lines measuring 200 mm. Although this codex is also attributed to ʿAlī b. Abī Ṭālib, it is more likely that it is the work of 2nd-3rd centuries. It is mentioned that the missing leaves after L. 412 were completed in Jumada al-awwal of 307 (919) by ʿAbd Allāh b. Muḥammad al-Ḥazrajī for Hizāname al-maʿmūrāt al-Zaynīya al-Nāblūsīya. L. 1b, 2a, 2b, 3a contain four plates decorated with Arabic-style geometrical patterns. L. 3b, 4a contain the sūras al-Fātiḥa and al-Baqara, where the beginning parts are written in gold and there are ornaments in Arabic style on the corners. Some of the [leaf] edges have been repaired with paper. Dark brown leather Ottoman binding with flap (miklep) and mandorla (şemse)."</p>
            </summary>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_706273" n="1">
              <title type="numeric" key="001:001:001-114:006:003">
                                    001:001:001-114:006:003
                                </title>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <extent>Folios: 414
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>272</width><height>195</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="16">16 - 16 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                kūfī
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate/>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>assistance: Salome Beridze</p>
                <p>metadata: Esra Gözeler</p>
                <p>metadata: Tuba Karaşahin</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <surface n="1" xml:id="mysql_id_61980">
                    </surface>
  </facsimile>
</TEI>
