<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_1437">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>London, The Khalili Collections, QUR 89</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
        <availability xml:id="imageRights-1" status="restricted" default="false">
          <p>Image credits: Nasser D. Khalili Collection of Islamic Art, Copyright Khalili Family Trust.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="48">The Khalili Collections
                            , London</repository>
            <idno>QUR 89</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary><p>111 fol.; Writing surface: paper; Shelfmark: QUR 89; Lines per page: 7-8;  Dimensions: 365 x 238 mm; Script style: New Style I; Estimated date of  production: 1000-1100.</p><p> </p>The catalogue written by François Déroche gives the following information about QUR 89 und <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/de/manuscripts/1438">QUR 89A</ref> (<ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/QJQEKNSJ" sameAs="QJQEKNSJ" type="zotero">Déroche, The Abbasid Tradition, London 1992</ref>, S. 156-60): "84 / Fragments of a 7-part Qur'an / 11th century AD / 122 folios (folio 1 is a modern blank), 36.5 x 23.8cm, with 8 lines to the page / <hi rend="italic">Material</hi> A hard, thick paper, laid, with 7-8 lines to the centimetre / <hi rend="italic">Text area</hi> 27.2 x 18cm, except on folios 3b-4b, where it is 25.5 x 18cm / <hi rend="italic">Script</hi> Style NS.I / <hi rend="italic">Accession nos </hi>QUR 89 (folios 1-10) and <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/de/manuscripts/1438">QUR 89A</ref> (folios 11-122) / <hi rend="italic">Published</hi> Christie's 16 June 1987, lot no. 77 (QUR 89 only) / <hi rend="italic">Comparative item </hi>Mashhad, Astan-i Quds Library, MS. 4316 (<ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/23CCS57V" sameAs="23CCS57V" type="zotero">Lings 1976</ref>, p. 18, pl. 11) / These pages once belonged to the first, sixth and seventh parts of a seven-part Qur'an that was clearly an impressive manuscript. The script is remarkable for its size, each line being roughly 4cm high. This presented the calligrapher (or calligraphers) with a considerable challenge, and his (or their) technical skills were not always good enough to meet it. Lapses occur mainly in the upstrokes; it is not unusual to find <hi rend="italic">alifs</hi> with an irregularly drawn shaft, for instance. There are also problems with the placing of what we consider to be the forerunner of the <hi rend="italic">tarwīs</hi>. In general, the script is close to that of a manuscript in Mashhad dated AH466 (AD1073-4; Astan-i Quds Library, MS.4316), although it is somewhat cruder. The calligraphy is quite homogeneous, except for a variation in the ending of final <hi rend="italic">mīm</hi>, but the evidence of the illumination suggests that more than one copyist was involved in the production of the manuscript (see below). / The material in the Khalili Collection is unequally drawn from the three parts. It includes an illuminated opening page and the following parts of the text: <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-f</hi><hi rend="italic">āti</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥah</hi> (I), verse 1, to <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-baqarah </hi>(II), verse 7 (folios 2b-3); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-baqarah</hi>, verses 13-19 (folio 4) and 54-74 (folios 5-10); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-fat</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥ </hi>(XLVIII), verses 17-29 (folios 11-16); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥujur</hi><hi rend="italic">āt </hi>(XLIX), verses 3-7 (folio 17); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥujur</hi><hi rend="italic">āt</hi>, verse 13, to <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-ṭ</hi><hi rend="italic">ūr </hi>(LII), verse 37 (folios 18-35); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-najm </hi>(LIII), verse 32, to <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-Ra</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥm</hi><hi rend="italic">ān</hi> (LV), verse 60 (folios 36-48); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-wāqiʿah </hi>(LVI), verse 44, to the heading of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-muj</hi><hi rend="italic">ādalah </hi>(LVIII; folios 49-61); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-muj</hi><hi rend="italic">ādalah</hi>, verses 4-12 (folios 62-4); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥashr </hi>(LIX), verses 9-12 (folio 65); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-jum</hi><hi rend="italic">ʿah </hi>(LXII), verse 1, to <hi rend="italic">Sūrat </hi><hi rend="italic">al-</hi><hi rend="italic">Ḥāqqah </hi>(LXIX), verse 19 (folios 66-95); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-N</hi><hi rend="italic">ū</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥ </hi>(LXXI), verse 1, to <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-mursal</hi><hi rend="italic">āt</hi> (LXXVII), verse 47 (folios 96-119); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-n</hi><hi rend="italic">ab</hi><hi rend="italic">āʾ </hi>(LXXVIII), verses 13-28 (folio 120); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-n</hi><hi rend="italic">āz</hi><hi rend="italic">iʿ</hi><hi rend="italic">āt </hi>(LXXIX), verses 14-30 (folio 121); <hi rend="italic">Sūrat Quraysh </hi>(CVI), verse 1, to the heading for <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-kawthar </hi>(CVIII; folio 122). The text is written in black ink, with diacritical strokes. The vowel signs, which have their modern form, are written in red. The orthoepic signs also have their modern form but have retained the colour of the dots used in the earlier manuscripts: green for <hi rend="italic">hamzah</hi> and <hi rend="italic">waṣlah</hi>, blue for shaddah, and yellow for <hi rend="italic">suk</hi><hi rend="italic">ūn</hi>. / Individual verses are punctuated by a 4.A.II ornament, with the number of the verse written out in gold in a script close to NS.I. The ground of the ornament usually varies from red to green to blue, but in some cases it is merely hatched. In the first part of the manuscript (folios 2b-10), the petals of the verse markers are smaller than in the remainder, where every tenth verse is followed by the same type of marker, with a letter indicating the number of verses in the <hi rend="italic">abjad</hi> system. A larger 3.D.II illumination in the margin gives the number of verses written out in gold script on a red, green or blue ground. A stylized <hi rend="italic">h</hi><hi rend="italic">āʾ </hi>shape, which is usually in gold but sometimes illuminated (see folio 103a), is set into the text after each group of five verses. It is complemented by a 3.D.II roundel in the margin. These roundels have a truncated base and a pointed top, and they contain the word <hi rend="italic">khams </hi>('five') in gold NS script on a red, green or blue ground. / The surah titles and verse counts are written in gold NS.I script on the coloured ground of a decorative band. The designs of the frames and grounds of these bands vary, but they are all accompanied by a vignette in the margin; these are mostly circular. The place of revelation is recorded below the vignette, and divisions of the text other than sevenths are also given in the margin. / The quires seem to consist of three bifolios. / This was rather an unusual arrangement in the Eastern Islamic world, but it is known from a number of manuscripts on parchment from the Maghrib. The ruling was done with a dry point on the open central bifolio. The two halves were thus ruled at the same time in folios 2-10 and 17-122; each of the remaining folios was ruled separately. Together with the variations in the illumination, this indicates that two calligraphers worked on the preparation of the seven volumes. A third piece of evidence is provided by the paper, for the laid lines in the paper used for folios 11-16 are clearly visible, while in the paper used for the other folios they cannot always be seen. It seems that the bifolios were made of two sheets glued together, as is often the case in early manuscripts on paper. / This Qur'an was richly illuminated. The available evidence suggests that each volume had an illuminated double-page frontispiece and finispiece. Half of the frontispiece of Part I has survived (folio 2a): it consists of the second part of a table of the components of the Qur'an - that is, the words, letters, diacritical dots and so on. The field has been divided into a chessboard pattern of six horizontal rows of three squares and is surrounded by two bands of interlace. In each of the squares, the number of words, letters or dots is given in NS script. In the central column, the script is in gold on a ground hatched in brown or sepia ink, and there are leaves or illuminations which resemble the verse markers. In the two outer columns, the script is reserved on a red and god, green and gold, or blue and gold ground with a vaguely vegetal design. The medial vignette is similar to types used in the manuscripts of earlier periods. A <hi rend="italic">basmalah</hi> has been added above the table. / The next double page (folios 2b-3a) contains the beginning of the text, <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-f</hi><hi rend="italic">āti</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥah </hi>and the first verses of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-baqarah. </hi>The layout suggests a certain clumsiness on the part of the calligrapher, who was unable to finish the text of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-f</hi><hi rend="italic">āti</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥah </hi>at the bottom of folio 2b and had to write the last word on folio 3a, but this did not affect the overall design of the illumination, whether or not it was carried out by the calligrapher. There is a slight imbalance between the two pages. Firstly, the bands at the top are not fully symmetrical, as the band on folio 3a contains the last word of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-f</hi><hi rend="italic">āti</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥah </hi>as well as the title of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-baqarah. </hi>This is written in gold, while the heading of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-f</hi><hi rend="italic">āti</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥah </hi>is reserved against the gold ground. Secondly, the illumination in the outer margins consists of two vertical rectangles on folio 2b, but there is only one on folio 3a. Each rectangle has an <hi rend="italic">ansa</hi> at the top and contains information about the surah and its place in the Qur'an. / The next full-page illumination is at the end of Part 6 (folio 15b-16a). The text, reduced to four lines to a page instead of eight, is written at the centre of the composition and is surrounded by gold strapwork. Above and below the text there is a wide illuminated band divided into three rectangles. These are decorated with chessboard designs of different sizes, the blue and white squares of the central rectangle being larger than the gold and black squares of the other two. This composition seems to have been inspired by illumination of an earlier period. On folio 16b, an almond-shaped design has been sketched out in black ink. / Like the verse markers and vignettes, the illumination varies slightly from one part of the manuscript to another. This variation can also be observed in the patterns used for the backgrounds of larger compositions: lattice patterns or horizontal hatching in the first part, oblique hatching in the rest. / The material from the last part of the manuscript preserved in the Khalili Collection provides evidence of the close relationship between calligrapher and illuminator, who was often the same person. On folio 38a, for instance, the last two words of <hi rend="italic">S</hi><hi rend="italic">ūrat al-najm </hi>are in blue ink and have been written one above the in the middle of the page; they were thus incorporated, along with the <hi rend="italic">sajdah</hi> ornament, in the illuminated band at the beginning of <hi rend="italic">S</hi><hi rend="italic">ūrat al-qamar</hi>. For this purpose, the band was divided into three square compartments. The end of <hi rend="italic">S</hi><hi rend="italic">ūrat al-najm </hi>occupies the central square, while the other two contain the title and the verse count of the following surah, which are reserved on the red and gold ground. The result is a fascinating balance between the text, which is arranged in three lines above and below the illumination, and the decoration itself."<p> </p><p>Unfortunately only a small selection of images from this manuscripts (as in the catalogue <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/QJQEKNSJ">Abbasid Tradition</ref>, p. 157-159, 161) are on display in this catalogue.</p>
                    </summary>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_687392" n="2r">
              <title type="numeric" key="001:001:000-001:001:000">
                                    001:001:000-001:001:000
                                </title>
            </msItem>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_687393" n="2v">
              <title type="numeric" key="001:001:001-001:007:008">
                                    001:001:001-001:007:008
                                </title>
            </msItem>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_687394" n="3r">
              <title type="numeric" key="002:001:001-002:004:005">
                                    002:001:001-002:004:005
                                </title>
            </msItem>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_687395" n="9r">
              <title type="numeric" key="002:065:011-002:068:003">
                                    002:065:011-002:068:003
                                </title>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="paper">
                <extent>Folios: 10
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>238</width><height>365</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="7 8">7 - 8 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                new style I
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate>1000-1100</origDate>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>assistance: Yunus C. Öç</p>
                <p>metadata: Michael Marx</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <surface n="2r" xml:id="mysql_id_47389">
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1437/fc23de1d-fd52-482d-acc3-2252656fc6c7/manuscript-1437-page-47389-image-33328.jpg"/>
    </surface>
    <surface n="2v" xml:id="mysql_id_47390">
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1437/bf5c4e0a-2412-45cf-9355-4b8e861b5791/manuscript-1437-page-47390-image-33329.jpg"/>
    </surface>
    <surface n="3r" xml:id="mysql_id_47391">
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1437/8c81d1ee-ef7b-4b00-bb0d-f19c32f8f5a4/manuscript-1437-page-47391-image-33330.jpg"/>
    </surface>
    <surface n="9r" xml:id="mysql_id_47392">
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1437/957918a6-8527-4749-a342-ab847b058c57/manuscript-1437-page-47392-image-33331.jpg"/>
    </surface>
  </facsimile>
</TEI>
