<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_1308">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Tbilisi, Georgian National Museum (საქართველოს ეროვნული მუზეუმი), sxm/ag. 2529</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="82">Georgian National Museum (საქართველოს ეროვნული მუზეუმი)
                            , Tbilisi</repository>
            <idno>sxm/ag. 2529</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
              <p>Single parchment folio, Shelfmark: sxm/ag. 2529; Qurʾānic Text: Q 4:127-135; Lines per page: 13; Dimensions: 345 x 240 mm; Script style: kūfī, variation of the type D.Va; Estimated date of production: 750-850. </p>
              <p> </p>
              <p>Originally sxm/ag. 2529 is probably from the same codex as <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/en/manuscripts/1364?sura=2&amp;amp;verse=221">HC.MS.03168</ref> and <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/handschriften/index/sure/6/vers/150?handschrift=1447">HC.MS.03113</ref> (Qatar National Library, Doha), <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/en/manuscripts/1786?sura=6&amp;amp;verse=19">AL-15</ref> (Library of Congress, Washington) as well as one folio in the <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/en/manuscripts/2981">Lausanne Collection</ref>. </p>
              <p> </p>
              <p>The catalogue of the Oriental collection of the Georgian Nationalmuseum has the following information about this fragment (<ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/ZEQ7BTGQ" sameAs="ZEQ7BTGQ" type="zotero">Oriental Collections of the Georgian National Museum, Irina Koshoridze (ed.), Tbilisi 2012, p. 59</ref>): "A fragment of a Qur'anic manuscript. Abbasid Caliphate. VIII-IX centuries. Parchment, ink, gold. 34.5 x 24 cm. Sxm/ag. 2529 presents one of the earliest pages of the Qurʾān. Sura 4 of the Qurʾān ("Women"), is written on parchment in a horizontal format in thirteen lines, which is typical of early examples. The kūfī calligraphic style of the Arabic script, diacritical marks - red dots and gold colored dividing rosettes are used." "ყურანის ხელნაწერის ფრაგმენტი. აბასიანთა სახალიფო. VIII-IX სს. პერგამენტი, მელანი, ოქრო. 34,5 x 24 სმ. სხმ/აღ. 2529 წარმოდგენილია ერთ-ერთი ადრეული ყურანის ფურცელი. ყურანის მე-4 სურა („ქალები“), შერსულებულია ჰორიზონტალური ფორმატის პერგამენტზე ცამეტ სტრიქონად, რაც ძირითადად ადრეული ნიმუშებისთვისაა დამახასიათებელი. გამოყენებულია არაბული დამწერლობის ქუფური კალიგრაფიული სტილი, დიაკრიტიკული ნიშნები - წითელი წერტილები და ოქროთი დაფერილი გამყოფი როზეტები." </p>
            </summary>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_706649" n="1r">
              <title type="numeric" key="004:127:001-004:130:009">
                                    004:127:001-004:130:009
                                </title>
            </msItem>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_682257" n="1v">
              <title type="numeric" key="004:130:010-004:135:019">
                                    004:130:010-004:135:019
                                </title>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <support>
                  <p><ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/en/manuscripts/1308/page/1r?sura=4&amp;verse=127">Recto</ref> is flesh side, <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/en/manuscripts/1308/page/1v?sura=4&amp;verse=130">verso</ref> is hair side. The text on the verso is better preserved than on the recto side. The structure of the quire is not known. </p>
                  <p> </p>
                  <p>Division of the text: There are single, fifth and tenth verse separators. Single verse separators consist of small gold rosettes. The tenth verse separator preserved on the <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/en/manuscripts/1308/page/1v?sura=4&amp;verse=130">verso</ref> side of the folio is a larger gold painted medallion, representing the end of verse number 130. Inside the ornament, <hi rend="italic">miʾa </hi><hi rend="italic">wa </hi><hi rend="italic">ṯalāṯūn</hi> (arabic: "130") is written. Red, green, yellow and blue pigments are used for the medallion. It should be noted that according to the Cairo edition the <hi rend="italic">taʿšīr</hi> marker is placed after the 131st verse. </p>
                </support>
                <extent>Folios: 1
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>345</width><height>240</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="13">13 - 13 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <summary>
                <p>The script of this Qurʾān fragment represents the <hi rend="italic">kūfī</hi> script style D being close to the D.Va group with elements of D.I/D.II as these subgroups are very similar <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/5RF6W5GJ" sameAs="5RF6W5GJ" type="zotero">(Déroche 1983: PN 112-116)</ref>, <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/QJQEKNSJ" sameAs="QJQEKNSJ" type="zotero">(Déroche 1992: PN 44-45)</ref>. The letter <hi rend="italic">ʾalif</hi> in the independent form has a long lower return with an upward curve. The letter <hi rend="italic">ǧīm</hi> in the medial form lies on the base line so that the letter before it is placed a little bit higher. In the final or independent position <hi rend="italic">ǧīm </hi>has a tail that curves back to the head of the letter close to the line, similar to the D.I/D.II group. The letter <hi rend="italic">ṭāʾ</hi> in the final or independent position is similar to those in the D.Va group. <hi rend="italic">ʿAyn</hi> initially resembles the D.Va group. In middle position, the letter shows a vertical right hand antenna which remains vertical in final position as well. <hi rend="italic">Qāf</hi> in its final or independent form shows a U-shaped tail that goes backwards as in D.II group. The letter <hi rend="italic">mīm </hi>in middle and final position is closer to D.II and D.III group. In both positions the letter lies rather flat on the line, in final position it has a short flat tail. <hi rend="italic">Nūn</hi> in final and independent position has a long body and the head is shorter than in D.I, being closer to D.III. <hi rend="italic">Hāʾ</hi> in the medial position is placed on the base line, the two eyes are mostly defined. The shape of the letter, which resembles a drop is close to the D.Va group. The <hi rend="italic">lām</hi>-<hi rend="italic">ʾalif </hi>ligature also resembles D.Va and D.I group, but the <hi rend="italic">lām</hi> is much thinner than <hi rend="italic">ʾalif </hi>and curves towards it.</p>
                <p>Unlike Déroche, we use the term <hi rend="italic">kūfī</hi> for pragmatic reasons - a term which is attested only after the 10th century. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Diacritics: Diacritica of the script are marked by oblique dashes in the same dark brown ink as the main text, mostly, the letters <hi rend="italic">bā</hi><hi rend="italic">ʾ </hi>and <hi rend="italic">nūn</hi> in final or independent position are marked. Vocalisation is indicated by red and green dots. Some lines show <hi rend="italic">mašq</hi>, horizontal stretching of the letters, a technique used to achieve a regular arrangement of letters within a line.</p>
              </summary>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                kūfī D.Va
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate>750-850</origDate>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>metadata: Salome Beridze</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <surface n="1r" xml:id="mysql_id_62342">
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1308/bbedbff4-3a97-4aaa-b6a9-80324946cd3c/manuscript-1308-page-62342-image-54233.jpg"/>
    </surface>
    <surface n="1v" xml:id="mysql_id_42263">
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1308/1596606b-1481-45b5-8773-a9aa8304573b/manuscript-1308-page-42263-image-33481.jpg"/>
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1308/f8f6b597-c778-42e1-810f-5bb003e32ff0/manuscript-1308-page-42263-image-54231.JPG"/>
    </surface>
  </facsimile>
</TEI>
