<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_2229">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Istanbul, Topkapı Palace Museum (Topkapı Sarayı Müzesi), A. 1 [= Karatay 6]</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="7">Topkapı Palace Museum (Topkapı Sarayı Müzesi)
                            , Istanbul</repository>
            <idno>A. 1 [= Karatay 6]</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
              <p>47 fol.; Writing surface: parchment; Shelfmark: A. 1; Text: Q 8:41-Q 9:93; 7 lines per page; Dimensions: 310 x 225 mm; Script style: kūfī; Estimated date of production: 2nd (8th) to 3rd (9th) centuries [according to Karatay]. </p>
              <p>This entry is based on the catalogue of Fehmi E. Karatay (1888-1968). Currently we do not have access to the images. With exceptions, the catalogue does not contain precise information on the distribution of the text throughout the pages. For this reason, only fol. 1 is given. </p>
              <p><ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/UEN2FUP7" sameAs="UEN2FUP7" type="zotero">Karatay (1962)</ref> describes the manuscripts as follows, p. 2-3: "6 A. 1 Kur’an’dan bir bölüm Parşömen. 225mm boy ve 310mm eninde cönk şeklinde 47 yaprak. Sahifede iri kûfi yazı ile 235mm uzunl.[uğunda] 7 satır. Tahminen hicrî II-III (VIII-IX) asırlarda yazılmıştır. Son yaprağın arkasına ketebehu ʿOs̠mān ibn ʿAffān fī sana diye yazılmış ise de bunun sonradan uydurulmuş olduğu şüphesizdir. Miklepli koyu kahve rengi deri cildin dışı sıva yıldız ve kabartma hendisi ve nebatı tezyınatı havidir; kapakların iç tarafları yaldız zemin üzerine rumî oymalı madalyon ve köşeliglidir; arkası ve mıklepsırtı tamir görmüştür. Sonuna ilâve edilmiş [k]âğıt yaprağın yüzünde III. Aḥmed’in vakıf mührü vardır.</p>
              <p>Bu Kur’an parçası Anfāl (8) suresinin 41. ayetinden واعلموا أنما غنمتم من شي den başlar. Y. 8b ile 9a arasında aynı surenin 58. ayetinden 66. ayetine kadar eksiktir; Y. 13b ile Y. 14a arasında bir yaprak eksiktir; Y. 14a da Tavbe (9) suresinin (ر)سوله فإن تبتم فهو خير لكم ayeti ile devam ediyor; Y. 32b ile 33a arası aynı surenin 49. ayetinin وإن جهنم لمحيطة بالكافرين kadar eksiktir; Y. 41b ile Y. 42aarasında aynı surenin 71 ayetinin cümlesinden 74. ayete kadar; Y. 45b ile 46a arasında 86. ayetin başından 89. ayete kadar eksiktir. Bundan sonra aynı surenin 93. ayetinin sonuna kadar vardır."</p>
              <p> </p>
              <p>This can be translated as follows: "6 A. 1 A part of the Qurʾān Parchment. 47 junk shaped leaves of 225 mm height and 310 mm width. The text area written in large Kufic script [contains] 7 lines measuring 235 mm. Probably copied during 2nd-3rd (8th-9th) centuries. Although, on the backside of the last leaf, “katabahu ʿUthmān ibn ʿAffān fī sana” is recorded, it is undoubtedly invented later. Dark brown leather binding with flap (miklep) has sıva yıldız, embossed geometric and plant illuminations on it. Inside covers are decorated with Rumi-carved medallions on gilded ground and contain corner pieces. Back cover and outside case of the flap (miklep) have been repaired. There is the foundation seal of Ahmad III on the front side of the paper sheet added at the end.</p>
              <p>The fragment begins with the words واعلموا أنما غنمتم من شي of Q 8:41 (Sūra al-ʾAnfāl). The verses from 58 to 66 of the same sūra are missing between L. 8b and 9a. One leaf is missing between L. 13b and 14a. 14a continues with the words (ر)سوله فإن تبتم فهو خير لكم of Q 9 (Sūra al-Tawba). Between L. 32b and 33a the verses up to the words وإن جهنم لمحيطة بالكافرين of verse 49 of the same sūra are missing. Between L. 41b and L. 42a the verses from 71 to 74 are missing. The verses from the beginning of verse 86 to 89 are missing between 45b and 46a. After that it contains until the end of the verse 93."</p>
            </summary>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_706260" n="1">
              <title type="numeric" key="008:041:001-009:093:019">
                                    008:041:001-009:093:019
                                </title>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <extent>Folios: 47
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>310</width><height>225</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="7">7 - 7 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                kūfī
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate/>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>assistance: Salome Beridze</p>
                <p>metadata: Esra Gözeler</p>
                <p>metadata: Tuba Karaşahin</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <surface n="1" xml:id="mysql_id_61967">
                    </surface>
  </facsimile>
</TEI>
