<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_1010">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>London, The Khalili Collections, QUR 372</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="48">The Khalili Collections
                            , London</repository>
            <idno>QUR 372</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
              <p>Déroche schreibt zu dem Fragment (vgl. <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/QJQEKNSJ" sameAs="QJQEKNSJ" type="zotero">The Abbasid Tradition, London 1992, S. 73</ref>): "24 / Part 2 of a 30-part Qurʾan / North Africa or Egypt, end of 9th century AD / 99 folios, 20.6x28.2 cm, with 6 lines to the page / <hi rend="italic">Material </hi>Parchment / <hi rend="italic">Text area</hi> 10.4x19.2 cm / <hi rend="italic">Script </hi>Style D.II / <hi rend="italic">Documentation </hi>An attribution as a record of ownership / <hi rend="italic">Binding </hi>Modern / <hi rend="italic">Accession no.</hi> QUR372 / <hi rend="italic">Comparative material</hi> This volume may belong to the same set as Copenhagen, Royal Library, C.I (Lindenberg 1830, pl. IX); Istanbul, Topkapı Palace Library, MSS EH 25, EH 26 (folio 21) and EH 28 (Karatay 1962, nos 32 and 35); and Paris, Bibliothèque Nationale, MS. arab. 349e (Déroche 1983, no. 114, and pl. XVb) / One of the most obvious characteristics of the D.II script is the way that the upper parts of letters such as <hi rend="italic">alif </hi>are bent slightly to the left. Another is the shape of final <hi rend="italic">nūn</hi>, which is quite close to that of D.I but is written in a coarser manner. / This manuscript offers an extensive example of the type of decoration used with this script. With one exception (a frame at the end of the Topkapı MS.EH 28), the material previously available contained only verse markers and vignettes, whereas cat. 24 opens and closes with double pages of illumination (folios 1b-2a and 98b-99a), and the first and last pages of text (folios 2b-3a and 97b-98a) are written within a frame from which a median spearhead-shaped vignette projects into the outer vertical margins. The designs of the four full-page illuminations are all different, but they are all based on the quotient of the golden rectangle. Ruling seems to be limited to the outer frame of the illumination (see folios 98 and 99). / The first panel, that on folio 1b, measures 11.4x18.4 cm and contains an interlace pattern of gold circles spread over a field 9.6x16.9 cm. Three horizontal and five vertical rows of larger circles form the outline of the design and are either tangent or secant with smaller circles. Various coloured dots are scattered between the gold fillets that form the circles. A gold fillet running over a row of small overlapping circles drawn in ink and surrounded by coloured dots serves as a frame. / The panel on the facing page (11.6x18.6 cm; field, 10,3x17.2 cm) contains an interlace pattern which combines circles and straight lines. Outwardly, there seem to be four horizontal and eight vertical double gold fillets cut by circles of various sizes; in fact, the larger circles are the result of the juxtaposition of large octagons with four curved sides. Four of the larger circles in each horizontal row have been filled with green; they were selected so as to create staggered vertical rows. The frame is the same as that of folio 1b. / The illumination on folio 98b (11.1x18.1 cm; field, 9.6x16.5 cm) also relies on a pattern of interlacing circles, but here the diameter of the largest circles, which are emphasized by the use of double gold fillets, is greater, and there are only two rows of full circles. Again the frame is reduced to a gold fillet between coloured dots. On the opposite page (folio 99a), the illumination (11.1x16.4 cm; field, 9.6x16.4 cm) uses a very different repertory: circles still play a role, but a very subdued one. Two bands defined by double gold fillets form a continuous pattern of interlace which creates a complex cable effect in the field. The frame is the same as that in the other designs. / The median vignettes are closely related in shape, in the repertory of motifs employed and in the peculiar form of stem they share. / Part 2 of a 20-part Qurʾan should contain verses 142-252 of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-baqarah</hi> (II), but the loss of the leaf that lay between folios 78 and 79 means that verse 232 is missing. The text is written in dark brown in, with the vocalization indicated by red dots. A peculiar 3.1.1 device separates the verses. There is a gold Kufic <hi rend="italic">hāʾ </hi>at the end of every fifth verse, and a 3.C.1 device at the end of every tenth verse. / Most of the quires have ten folios, but the first has seven folios, the last has four, and there are two nine-folio quires, one of which (folio 77 onwards) has lost one leaf. Hair sides face flesh sides, as is usual, and the quires begin with the hair side on the outside. / A note on folio 1a attributes the copying of this manuscript to Hasan, while another note on the verso of the same leaf records that the volume was once property of Muʿizz al-Din Muhammad al-Mansuri al-Husayni." </p>
            </summary>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <extent>Folios: 99
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>282</width><height>206</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="6">6 - 6 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                kūfī D.II
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate/>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>metadata: Michael Marx</p>
                <p>assistance: Johanna Schubert</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>(No content available)</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
