<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_1286">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Los Angeles, California, Los Angeles County Museum of Art, M.86.196</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
        <availability xml:id="imageRights-1" status="restricted" default="false">
          <p>Image credits: LACMA.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="64">Los Angeles County Museum of Art
                            , Los Angeles, California</repository>
            <idno>M.86.196</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
              <p>Folio of the Blue Qurʾān, Shelfmark: M.86.196; Qurʾānic Text: 4:23-25;  Lines per page: 15; Dimensions: 283 x 375 mm; Script style: kūfī, type  D; Estimated date of production: 800-1000. </p>
              <p>The <ref target="https://collections.lacma.org/node/252330">website of Los Angeles County Museum has the following information</ref> (retrieved on June 14th 2021): "Page from a Manuscript of the Qur'an (4:23-24; 4:24-25) Tunisia, probably Qairawan, late 9th-early 10th century Manuscripts; folios Gold leaf, silver, and ink on parchment colored with indigo 11 1/8 x 14 3/4 in. Frame: 29 × 23 × 1 1/2 in. (73.66 × 58.42 × 3.81 cm) The Nasli M. Heeramaneck Collection, gift of Joan Palevsky (M.86.196) Art of the Middle East: Islamic and Contemporary Not currently on public view Curator Notes With its distinctive blue color and use of gold and silver ink for the script, this page can be readily identified as coming from a manuscript known as the Blue Qur’an, which is dispersed among several collections in North America, Europe, and the Middle East but survives primarily in Tunisia, where it was probably made. While this Qur’an is so far unique among Islamic manuscripts due to its coloration, it does share similarities with Byzantine manuscripts that used purple parchment with metallic inks. Less.. Bibliography      Evans, Helen C. and Brandie Ratliff, ed. Byzantium and Islam: Age of Transition, 7th-9th Century. New York: Metropolitan Museum of Art, 2012.      Lo Terrenal y lo Divino: Arte Islámico siglos VII al XIX Colección del Museo de Arte del Condado de Los Ángeles. Santiago: Centro Cultural La Moneda, 2015.     Bloom, Jonathan M. "The Blue Koran Revisited." Journal of Islamic Manuscripts v.6, no.2-3 (2015): 196-218.     Komaroff, Linda. Beauty and Identity: Islamic Art from the Los Angeles County Museum of Art. Los Angeles: Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 2016.     Keene, Bryan C., editor. Toward a Global Middle Ages: Encountering the World Through Illuminated Manuscripts. Los Angeles: The J. Paul Getty Museum, 2019.      Pal, Pratapaditya, Thomas W. Lentz, Sheila R. Canby, Edwin Binney, 3rd, Walter B. Denny, and Stephen Markel. "Arts from Islamic Cultures: Los Angeles County Museum of Art." Arts of Asia 17, no. 6 (November/December 1987): 73-130.     Los Angeles County Museum of Art.  New York: Thames and Hudson, 2003.     Komaroff, Linda.  Islamic Art at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art.  Los Angeles:  Museum Associates, 2005.     Blair, Shelia S. Islamic Calligraphy. Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2006.      Bloom, Jonathan and Sheila Blair, eds. And Diverse Are Their Hues: Color in Islamic Art and Culture. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2011"  </p>
              <p>For an updated overview of sister fragments, see the detailed catalogue  entry by Marcus Fraser on a sister fragment of the Blue Qurʾān kept by <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/handschriften/index/sure/2/vers/286/handschrift/1458">Qatar National Library, call number HC.MS. 03223</ref>.</p>
            </summary>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_681107" n="1r">
              <title type="numeric" key="004:023:011-004:024:015">
                                    004:023:011-004:024:015
                                </title>
            </msItem>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_681108" n="1v">
              <title type="numeric" key="004:024:016-004:025:033">
                                    004:024:016-004:025:033
                                </title>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <extent>Folios: 1
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>283</width><height>375</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="15">15 - 15 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                kūfī D
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate>800-1000</origDate>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>metadata: Michael Marx</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <surface n="1r" xml:id="mysql_id_41141">
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1286/af14f7da-0ca0-43e3-8619-677d74e76cd6/manuscript-1286-page-41141-image-26446.tiff"/>
    </surface>
    <surface n="1v" xml:id="mysql_id_41142">
      <graphic decls="#imageRights-1" url="manuscript/1286/7d59bab0-b220-4303-bc97-eed78df1c806/manuscript-1286-page-41142-image-26447.tiff"/>
    </surface>
  </facsimile>
</TEI>
