<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_2247">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Istanbul, Topkapı Palace Museum (Topkapı Sarayı Müzesi), E. H. 1 [= Karatay 24]</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="7">Topkapı Palace Museum (Topkapı Sarayı Müzesi)
                            , Istanbul</repository>
            <idno>E. H. 1 [= Karatay 24]</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
              <p>322 fol.; Writing surface: parchment; Shelfmark: E. H. 1; Text: Complete Qur'an (?); 18 lines per page; Dimensions: 210 x 180 mm; Script style: kūfī; Estimated date of production: 2nd (8th) to 3rd (9th) centuries [according to Karatay]. </p>
              <p>This entry is based on the catalogue of Fehmi E. Karatay (1888-1968). Currently we do not have access to the images. With exceptions, the catalogue does not contain precise information on the distribution of the text throughout the pages. For this reason, only fol. 1 is given. </p>
              <p><ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/corpuscoranicum_pub/items/itemKey/UEN2FUP7" sameAs="UEN2FUP7" type="zotero">Karatay (1962)</ref> describes the manuscripts as follows, p. 8: "24 E. H. 1 Aynı Parşömen. 180mm boy ve 210mm eninde cönk şeklinde 322 yaprak. Sahifede kûfî ile 185mm uzunl.[uğunda] 18 satır. Bu mushafın Y. 1b deki altınla yazılı tasdik ve izahatta Ḫalīfe ʿOs̠mān b. ʿAffān tarafından yazıldığı yazılı ise de H. II - III. asır yazısı olması ihtimali çok daha kuvvetlidir. Ayni izahta bunun 600 (1262) yılında Musul kadısının elinde bulunduğu zaman baş tarafından sekiz yaprağın telef olduğu, bilahire Şama naklolunan bu mushafın 740 (1340) Şevvalinin 26. gecesi vukua gelen bir yangında kitabın Y. 174 den 177 ye kadar dört yaprağı yanmış olduğunu ve sonra VIII. asır neshi ile Fātiḥa (1) suresi ile Baḳara (2) suresinin 151. ayetinin يعلمكم الكتاب والحكمة ويعلمكم ibaresine kadar olan kısmın ilâve edildiğini öğreniyoruz. Bundan başka Mushafın bir çok yaprakların[ın] silinmiş olan yazıları üzerine Arap nesi ile yeniden yazıldığı görülüyor. Başdaki tasdiki havi olan sahifesinin etrafı üç sıra zencirekli ve yaldızlı bir kitabe ve Y. 2a da sahifesinin üstünde lacivert zemin üzerine beyazla انه لقرآن كريم ... ayeti yazılmış ve rumilerle tezhip edilmiştir. Cildi miklepli deri olup kapaklarında yaldızla hendesî tezyinat ve mıklep sırtında هذا المصحف بحط الامام عثمان بن عفان ... ibaresi yazılıdır."</p>
              <p>This can be translated as follows: "24 E. H. 1 Same Parchment. 322 junk shaped leaves of 180 mm height and 210 mm width. The text area written in Kufic script [contains] 18 lines measuring 185 mm. According to the golden imprimatur and record on L. 1b, it is said that [this codex] is copied by Caliph ʿUthmān b. ʿAffān. But it is significantly more likely that it is a 2nd-3rd AH century script. We learn from the same record that eight leaves from the beginning of this [codex] were destroyed when it was in the hands of the judge of Mosul in 600 (1262). And those four pages of this codex, from L. 174 to 177, which was later transferred to Damascus, were burned in a fire that occurred on the 26th night of Shawwal 740 (1340). Later, Q 1 (Sūrah al-Fātiḥah) and the part until يعلمكم الكتاب والحكمة ويعلمكم of verse Q 2:151 (Sūra al-Baqarah) were added with the naskh of 8th century. Moreover, it is seen that many leaves of the codex are rewritten with Arabic naskh on the vague texts. The leaf at the beginning containing the imprimatur is decorated with a gilded inscription which is surrounded by a three-line guilloche (zencirek). And on L. 2a, the verse انه لقرآن كريم ... is written in white on a dark blue background and decorated with rumi. Leather binding with flap (miklep), gilded geometric ornaments on the cover. هذا المصحف بحط الامام عثمان بن عفان ... is written on the spine of the flap (miklep)."</p>
            </summary>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_706272" n="1">
              <title type="numeric" key="001:001:001-114:006:003">
                                    001:001:001-114:006:003
                                </title>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <extent>Folios: 322
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>210</width><height>180</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="18">18 - 18 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                kūfī
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate/>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>assistance: Salome Beridze</p>
                <p>metadata: Esra Gözeler</p>
                <p>metadata: Tuba Karaşahin</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <surface n="1" xml:id="mysql_id_61979">
                    </surface>
  </facsimile>
</TEI>
