<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mysql_id_2389">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Saint Petersburg, The National Library of Russia (Российская национaльная библиотeка), Marcel 85</title>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository key="23">The National Library of Russia (Российская национaльная библиотeка)
                            , Saint Petersburg</repository>
            <idno>Marcel 85</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
              <p>5 fol. on parchment; Shelfmark: Marcel 85; Qurʾānic Text: Q 1:1-1:7, Q  58:2-58:4; 5 lines per page; Dimensions: 244 x 177mm; Script style:  kūfī  D.I / D.III.  </p>
              <p> </p>
              <p>The fragments <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/de/manuscripts/2380">Marcel 50</ref>, <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/de/manuscripts/2401">Marcel 88</ref> and <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/de/manuscripts/2402">Marcel 89</ref> (NLR) belong to the same manuscript. Fol. 8 of Marcel 50 directly follows fol. 5 of this manuscript. </p>
              <p> </p>
              <p>This entry was created on the basis of the information made available  by Valery V. Polosin (1939-2014), without use of manuscript images.  Therefore, the exact distribution of the Qurʾānic passages across the  manuscript pages is unknown to us, and all the passages are shown as  belonging to fol. 1. The catalogue entry by Polosin contains the following information:</p>
              <p>"<hi rend="bold">Mar</hi><hi rend="bold">cel 85</hi></p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Two fragments</hi>: <hi rend="bold">1</hi>:1(1–2)–7(7); <hi rend="bold">58</hi>:2(2)–5(4). </p>
              <p>5 fol. 177×244 mm (1.38). <hi rend="bold">Support</hi>: thin transparent parchment, rigid and smooth, of yellowish color. <hi rend="bold">Writing </hi><hi rend="bold">material</hi>: brown ink.</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Collation</hi>: fragments of one quire, with fol. 2 and 5 being a bifolium, the rest – singltons with stubs. This is probably the beginning quire of <hi rend="italic">juz’</hi> 28 in which surah 1 is immediately followed by surah 58.</p>
              <p>I: H1F H2F H3F<hi rend="italic"> S</hi> / F4H<hi rend="italic"> S F5H S</hi></p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Text layout</hi>: 78×157 mm (2.0), 5 lines. <hi rend="bold">Ruling</hi>: absent; on fol. 1-2 there are visible embossed traces of layout for an illuminated frontispiece applied with a hard-point tool.<hi rend="bold"> Script</hi>: small-scale, D I / D III.<hi rend="bold"> Diacritics</hi>: diagonal dashes in the same ink as the main text. <hi rend="bold">Vocalization</hi>: dots in red paint of different shades; large and uneven green and blue dots.</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Verse markers</hi>: for individual verses – rosettes (type 3.1.2) in gold an colors; for groups of five verses – medallions on the margins (type 4.A.II) in gold and colors, with the inscribed word  خمس(fol. 3v).</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Frontispiece (fol. 1r)</hi> shaped by two rectangular frames, one inscribed into another, drawn qith gold with the addition of red and green paint. The outer one (measured 80×161 mm) is formed by entrelacs pattern; the inner one (measured 41×122 mm) – zigzag pattern. Area between the two frames is filled with floral patterns drawn in pale light-brown ink; inside the inner frame there is an inscription contoured with the same pale ink. Large golden palmetto on the outer margin outlined with blue paint.</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Double-page frontispiece (fol. 1v-2r)</hi>, with a rectangular panel on each page filled with bold interlacing geometric patterns, with large palmettos outlined with blue paint on the outer margins.</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Title of surah 1</hi> (فاتحة الكتاب سبع ايات) on fol. 2v is outlined with gold and inscribed in the rectangular panel occupying the entire line, filled with floral design drawn in gold over the red background above the title and over the green background below it; with large golden palmetto outlined with blue paint on the outer margin.</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Stitching</hi>: thread has preserved in the punctures of the fold of fol. 3.</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Inscriptions</hi>: numbers of the surahs in Roman numerals and the verse numbers in Arabic numerals are inscribed in ink on the upper margins of all pages; verse numbers are also marked in the text; on the lower margin of fol. 4r there is an inscription in French, in pencil; inscription “ب عليهم” on the lower margin of fol. 3v, written in a European hand, serves as a catchword.</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Traces of old conservation</hi>: outer margins have been trimmed.</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Defects</hi>: upper outer corners damaged and darkened; a hole on fol. 1; traces of moisture along the folds; ink has partly peeled off on the flesh sides.</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Attached materials</hi>: old wrapping (fol. I) consisting of a narrow strip of paper inscribed with the letters “<hi rend="italic">C</hi>”, brief description of the manuscript in French in brown ink and old accession number in red pencil “<hi rend="italic">B. 62”; on the verso side inscription in French “Quai des Grands Augustins 27”. </hi></p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Old accession numbers</hi>: С (on the wrapping); B. 62 (on the wrapping and according to Langlois’ inventory).</p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Contents</hi>:</p>
              <p>Fol. 1r–2r. Inlluminated frontispieces.</p>
              <p>Fol. 2v–3v. Surah 1, verses 1(1–2)–7(7). Incipit: بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم  . Explicit:  غير المغضو[ب عليهم].</p>
              <p>Fol. 4r–5v. Surah 58, verses 2(2)–5(4). Incipit: [ليقولون] منكراً من القول . Explicit: لتؤمنوا بالله ورسوله [وتلك حدود الله] . </p>
              <p><hi rend="bold">Other fragments of the same manuscript</hi>: Marcel 50 (fol. 8 immediately follows fol. 5 of Marcel 855), Marcel 88, Marcel 89 (NLR)."</p>
              <p> </p>
              <p>Olga Yastrebova has translated and sometimes corrected the notes of V. Polosin. Corrected passages are marked with ОЯ (O.Ya).</p>
              <p> </p>
              <p>An image of an ornamental page and a detail image of a verse marker can be seen on the <ref target="https://expositions.nlr.ru/eng/ex_manus/Koran/list.php">website of the NLR</ref> (No. 9 and 16).</p>
            </summary>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_707880" n="1">
              <title type="numeric" key="001:001:001-001:007:006">
                                    001:001:001-001:007:006
                                </title>
            </msItem>
            <msItem xml:id="mysql_id_707881" n="1">
              <title type="numeric" key="058:002:016-058:004:020">
                                    058:002:016-058:004:020
                                </title>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc>
              <supportDesc material="parchment">
                <extent>Folios: 5
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><width>244</width><height>177</height></dimensions>
                                </extent>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="5">5 - 5 lines to a page
                                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote/>
            </handDesc>
            <scriptDesc>
              <scriptNote>
                                                                kūfī D.I / D.III
                            </scriptNote>
            </scriptDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate/>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <p>assistance: Karina Söhl</p>
                <p>metadata: Valery V. Polosin (1939-2014)</p>
              </recordHist>
              <availability>
                <p/>
              </availability>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <surface n="1" xml:id="mysql_id_76746">
                    </surface>
  </facsimile>
</TEI>
