<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tuk_doi">
  <!--add the DOI here!-->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Niketas von Byzanz, Ἀνατροπὴ τοῦ Κορανίου ("Widerlegung des Koran"), Conf. I, lin. 81–92, Conf. XVIII, lin. 143–152</title>
        <title/>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <date calendar="#Gregorian">19-12-2024</date>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
        <idno type="tuk_DOI">askxxx</idno>
        <!--the DOI could be repeated here-->
        <idno type="instID">askxxx</idno>
        <!--CCint.institutional ID-->
        <idno type="CCTUKID"/>
        <!--CCint.msID-->
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:id="tuk_1636" xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>Corpus Coranicum</repository>
            <idno>1636</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>Entnommen aus: Ulbricht 2021, S. 1365-1368.Niketas’ Ausführungen über das koranische Hapaxlegomenon aṣ-ṣamad (Q 112:2) sind für das frühe Koranverständnis im Arabischen von Relevanz (vgl. zu diesem Terminus: Simelidis 2011). Er nimmt dieses Lexem als Ausgangspunkt für Überlegungen über die Beschaffenheit Gottes im Koran, also dessen Natur im engeren Sinne (Förstel 2000, Conf. I, 81–86; XVIII, 144–148). Eine entsprechende Diskussion um den Anthropomorphismus Gottes im Koran entsteht auch bei muslimischen Gelehrten in jener Zeit, vgl. Holtzman 2011). Im einleitenden Teil seiner Widerlegung widerspricht der Byzantiner der vermeintlich koranischen Aussage, „dass kugelförmig das Göttliche ist“ (ὅτι σφαιρικόν ἐστι τὸ θεῖον) – vielmehr noch, „wie er [scil. Muhammad] selbst sagte, dass Gott eine Vollkugel ist“ (ὡς αὐτὸς εἶπεν, ὁλόσφαιρός ἐστιν ὁ Θεὸς) [Zitate: Förstel 2000, Conf. I, 81–82 bzw. I, 82]. Denn eine Kugelgestalt setze Materialität voraus [Conf. I, 83: οὐ γὰρ ἂν ἄλλως τὸ τῆς σφαίρας ἐδέχεται σχῆμα („denn anders hätte er die Kugelgestalt nicht annehmen können“, Förstel 2000, S. 45); Förstel 2000, Conf. I, 84: σφαῖρα δὲ ὑλικὴ κατ’ αὐτὸν τυγχάνων („nach ihm eine materielle Kugel seiend“)]. Niketas’ Widerspruch richtet sich an dieser Stelle (Förstel 2000, Conf. I, 81–86) demnach gegen eine ,Kugelgestalt‘ Gottes, da dadurch Muhammad „als Körper gänzlich ihn [scil. Gott] sich vorstellen“ würde (σῶμα πάντως αὐτὸν οἰόμενος) [Förstel 2000, Conf. I, 82–83].Am Ende seiner Koranpolemik wiederum zitiert Niketas Sure 112 wörtlich aus der ihm vorliegenden Übersetzung, wobei das Wort aṣ-ṣamad (Q 112:2) im Coranus Graecus (CG), d. h. der in Niketas’ Text überlieferten Version der griechischen Koranübersetzung, als ὁλόσφυρος übersetzt wird [Förstel 2000, Conf. XVIII, 145–146; Zitat: Förstel 2000, Conf. XVIII, 146 („undurchdringlich“, Förstel 2000, S. 117)]. Diesen Terminus wiederum hermeneutisiert Niketas wie folgt: Εἰ μὴ τὸ σχῆμα τῆς σφαίρας δηλοῖ τὸ ὁλόσφυρον, ἀλλά γε τὸ πυκνὸν καὶ πεπιλημένον [Förstel 2000, Conf. XVIII, 147–148: „Wenn das Wort ,undurchdringlich‘ auch nicht die Kugelgestalt bezeichnet, so doch das Dichte und Feste“ (Förstel 2000, S. 117–119)]. Auch dies impliziere eine Materialität, da „auch das [Dichte und Feste] eine Eigenschaft des Körpers“ sei (καὶ αὐτὸ τοῦ σώματος ἴδιον) [Förstel 2000, Conf. XVIII, 148].Niketas zielt darauf ab, das muslimische Gottesbild als ein materielles des eigentlich metaphysischen Gottes zu interpretieren. In quellenkritischer Hinsicht ist bemerkenswert, dass das Wort aṣ-ṣamad (Q 112:2), welches in den zwei verschiedenen Textpassagen in Niketas’ Werk Ausgangspunkt der Diskussion ist (Förstel 2000, Conf. I, 81–86 bzw. Conf. XVIII, 144–148), jeweils unterschiedlich im Griechischen wiedergegeben wird:QuelleVokabelInterpretation durch NiketasNiketasσφαιρικόν (I, 81)ὁλόσφαιρος (I, 82)τὸ τῆς σφαίρας ἐδέχεται σχῆμα (I, 83); σφαῖρα δὲ ὑλικὴ κατ’ αὐτὸν τυγχάνων (I, 84); σῶμα πάντως αὐτὸν οἰόμενος· (I, 82–83)CG     ὁλόσφυρος (XVIII, 146)τὸ ὁλόσφυρον (XVIII, 147)εἰ μὴ τὸ σχῆμα τῆς σφαίρας δηλοῖ τὸ ὁλόσφυρον ἀλλά γε τὸ πυκνὸν καὶ 
πεπιλημένον, ὅπερ καὶ αὐτὸ τοῦ σώματος ἴδιον. (XVIII, 147–148)Zu beachten ist, dass es sich um zwei Vokabeln aus wohl ursprünglich zwei unterschiedlichen Quellen handelt (s. Trapp 1980), welche uns in einem einzigen Tradenten (Vat.gr. 681) überliefert sind: Während die in Förstel 2000, Conf. I, 81–86 angestoßene Diskussion auf Niketas als Autor selbst zurückgehen dürfte, zitiert er in Förstel 2000, Conf. XVIII, 144–146 wohl wörtlich aus der griechischen Koranübersetzung selbst. Dies darf auch als Indiz gelten, dass Niketas die griechische Übersetzung des Korans sehr wörtlich übernommen hat. Das ist nicht mit der Beobachtung im Widerspruch zu sehen, dass Niketas eigenmächtig mit der ihm vorliegenden Übersetzung verfährt, d. h., dass er koranische Inhalte für seine Zwecke benutzt, indem er sie für seine polemischen Ziele selektierend verwendet. Vielmehr ist hiermit gesagt, dass Niketas an den Stellen, an welchen er aus der Koranübersetzung zitiert, sehr getreu die Vorlage übernimmt. Dennoch ist aus den Kontexten deutlich, dass beide Passagen (Förstel 2000, Conf. I, 81–86 und Conf. XVIII, 144–148) auf Q 112:2 zurückgehen. Obgleich Niketas nicht explizit auf die unterschiedlichen Vokabeln hinweist, versucht er dennoch beide verwendeten Termini – σφαιρικός bzw. ὁλόσφαιρος (Förstel 2000, Conf. I, 81.82: ,kugelhaft‘ bzw. ,ganz-kugelförmig‘) einerseits und ὁλόσφυρος [Förstel 2000, Conf. XVIII, 146.147: ,undurchdringlich‘ (nach Förstel 2000, 117)] andererseits – inhaltlich miteinander zu harmonisieren (siehe oben tabellarische Gegenüberstellung, Spalte „Interpretation durch Niketas“). Im Gesamtkontext der Widerlegung wird dieser Diskussion jedoch mit gut zehn Editionszeilen kein übergroßer Raum zugesprochen (bei durchschnittlich ca. 40 Editionszeilen auf 40 Seiten griechischen Texts [ed. Förstel 2000, 40–120, einseitig, à ø 40 Zeilen/Seite] = 1.600 Editionszeilen).RezeptionNiketas’ Polemik scheint in der Verwendung von Übersetzungen des koranischen Hapaxlegomenon aṣ-ṣamad (Q 112:2) eine polydimensionale Diskussion hinsichtlich des Verständnisses dieses Terminus innerhalb der byzantinisch-apologetischen Literatur zu reflektieren: Er selbst verwendet den Begriff σφαιρικός bzw. ὁλόσφαιρος, den auch Manuel II. Palaiologos in die Aufzählung der Adjektive mit alpha privata seiner Beschreibung der Eigenschaften Gottes einfügt (Trapp 1966, 122, 4–8, hier Z. 5: οὐχ ὁλόσφαιρον, ὡς ὑμεῖς). Die griechische Koranübersetzung anonymer Autorschaft hingegen übersetzt aṣ-ṣamad mit ὁλόσφυρος, was nicht nur Niketas zitiert, sondern auch die Abuiratio (Montet 1906, 155, Z. 24–25), die ebenfalls einige wenige Fragmente jener Übersetzung überliefert. Darüber hinaus jedoch wird dieser Terminus sowohl in der anonymen Polemik Κατὰ Μωάμεδ (PG 104, Sp. 1447–1458: 1453C [Z. 8]) als auch bei Bartholomaios von Edessa (PG 104, Sp. 1383–1448: 1385C [Z. 14]) erwähnt, wobei beide nach Niketas von Byzanz verfasst worden sind. Somit muss nicht zwingend eine Abhängigkeit von der griechischen Koranübersetzung angenommen werden, vielmehr käme Niketas als Vorlage in Betracht. Bartholomaios führt zudem noch ein drittes Adjektiv zur Beschreibung des im Koran genannten Gottes ein (ὁλόβολος [,fest geschlagen‘ („beaten solid“, Lampe 1961, s.v.]), schreibt er doch in seinem Ἔλεγχος Ἀγαρηνοῦ:Καὶ αὐτὸ τὸ ὄνομα, οὗ ἀρχὴ ἐν αὐτοῦ Κουρανίου [sic] σου, ὅντινα ἐλεοῦντα καὶ ἐλεήμονα μὲν ἀποκαλεῖτε, οὗτοί ἐστιν οὓς καλεῖτε διὰ τῆς γλώττης ὑμῶν Ἀλὰχ, Σαμὲτ, Τζαμὲτ, τοῦτ’ ἔστιν προφανῶς ὁλόσφυρος, καὶ ὁλόβολος, οἷος κρατεῖται, καὶ σχῆμα ἔχει (PG 104, 1383–1448: 1385C [Z. 10–15]).Somit findet sich für die Verwendung der Übersetzung des arabischen aṣ-ṣamad (Q 112:2) in den genannten byzantinischen Polemiken folgende Aufteilung:ὁλόσφαιροςὁλόσφυρος    ὁλόβολοςNiketas (Förstel: I, 82)CG (Förstel: XVIII, 146.147)Bartholomaios (PG 104: 1385C, 14)Manuel II. (Trapp: 122,5)  Abiuratio (Montet: 155,24–25)Κατὰ Μωάμεδ (PG 104: 1453C, 8)Bartholomaios (PG 104: 1385C, 14)Zu Autor und Quelle:The very first Byzantine to refer to the Muslims’ Kalām Allāh (‘Word of God’) in its written manifestation, the Qur’ān, is Nicetas Byzantious (9th/10th century). In his polemical writing "Refutation of the Qur’ān", he is quoting a number of Qur’ān passages in different manners, ranging from literal and free quotations up to paraphrases and simple allusions. Undoubtedly, Nicetas had at his disposition a Greek translation of the Qur’ān, which must have been complete and in written form (cf. Ulbricht 2022, forthcoming). This translation was not his own but is from unknown authorship dating back to the 9th century terminus ante quem.Nicetas used the Greek translation of the Qur’ān in order to write an extensive polemic against Islam in a scholastic way. It is for the first time that the State Church of the Byzantine (East-Roman) Empire was engaged with the new religion from an official point of view. Former apologetics, such as John of Damascus and Theodore Abū Qurra, were rejecting Islam while living in the Muslim Caliphate itself. Their motivation was mostly a theological one. Nicetas Byzantious, in contrast, was part of the Empire’s elite in the capital Constantinople and his "Refutation" thus depicts an official statement of the East Roman Empire against Islam. This happened in the historical period of the 9th century when Byzantium was gaining back some of its lost forces during the Muslim futūḥāt ("conquests") in the 7th/8th century.The "Refutation of the Qur’ān" consists of an apologetic introduction, in which Nicetas explains the Orthodox faith, and a polemical main part, in which he refutes Islamic teachings. Nicetas’s polemic is especially important because it preserves a significant number of Qur’anic verses and narrations from a number of Qur’ānic suras in Greek. However, Nicetas used the Greek translation of the Qurʾān in order to write his extensive polemic against Islam.The "Refutation of the Qurʾān" is preserved in one single Greek manuscript, held today in the Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana (Vat. gr. 681), dating itself back to around 900 CE (Devresse 1950, 143–44; Rigo 2006, 149–150). The translation itself, which is now lost and partly preserved in Nicetas’s polemical work, seems to be the oldest complete translation of the Qurʾān ever, i.e., dating back to 9th century AD (2nd/3rd century hiǧrī) or potentially even before. This is extraordinarily close to the time of the genesis of the Qur’anic text and dates even prior to Ibn Muǧāhid’s canonization of the Seven Readings (qirāʾāt) in 934. It is, therefore, an important source for early hermeneutics of the Qur’an.There are three editions of Niketas’ text: the editio princeps by A. Mai 1847 (p. 321–408), the reprint of that edition in the Patrologia Graeca 105 (col. 665–806), and a modern, critical edition by K. Förstel 2000.In addition, two editions have extracted a number of Qurʾānic fragments from Nicetas’ work and published them individually: Förstel 2009 and Høgel 2010. For the text given, Förstel’s edition and translation of the "Refutation" is used.The fragments of the Qurʾānic translation which are first preserved in the form of Nicetas’ text and in the Abjuratio are called Coranus Graecus. This is the text form of the remnants of this translation as we have manuscript evidence.The work of Evodius the Monk, Euthymius Zigabenus, and Nicetas Choniates depend on Nicetas’ work and/or the Abjuratio. The dependencies and tradition between the Byzantine sources are still not clear. The preserved form of the Qurʾānic translation as in Nicetas’ work has to be differentiated from the original form of the original Greek translation of the Qurʾān, which actually only exists as a hypothetical text as the original is not preserved anymore.Trapp 1980 proved that the (anonymous) author(s) of the Qurʾān translation and Nicetas are two different persons. The study by Sahas 1995 examines the usage of the word Holosphyros across different Christian anti-Islamic polemical works. The article by Simelidis 2011 explores different translations of aṣ-ṣamad across Greek works dealing with Islam. The article by Ulbricht 2021 puts Nicetas’ work into a broader context and presents and analyzes Nicetas’ anti-Islamic argumentation. The forthcoming article by Ulbricht (JÖB 2022) proves that the original Greek translation must have been available to Nicetas as a complete version and in a written form. Über die Quelle: Datierung, Editionen etc.Quelle: Anonym Daten: unsicher; 10./11. Jahrhundert Ort: (?) Titel der Quelle: (Κατὰ Μωάμεδ, Kata Mōamed) = Gegen MuḥammadEditionen: J.-P. Migne, hrsg., Patrologia Graeca, vol. 104, Paris 1896, Sp. 1447–1458.Hier Seiten: J.-P. Migne, hrsg., Patrologia Graeca, vol. 104, Paris 1896, Sp. 1453.Griechischer Text: J.-P. Migne, hrsg., Patrologia Graeca, vol. 104, Paris 1896, col. 1453 B16–C13Λέγει περὶ τῆς πλάσεως τοῦ Ἀδὰμ, ἐν ᾑ φησιν, ὅτι ἐπλάσθη ὁ ἄνθρωπος ἀπὸ χώματος καὶ σταγόνος, καὶ ἤδελον, καὶ μασήματος, καὶ ὃτι τοῦ ἀνθρώπου πλασθέντος, οἱ μὲν ἄλλοι πάντες ἄγγελοι προστάξει Θεοῦ προσεκύνησαν αὐτοῦ. Μόνος δὲ ὁ Βελίαρ οὐκ ἐπείσθη προσκυνῆσαι τὸν Ἀδάμ, καὶ διὰ τοῦτο πέπτωκεν. Λέγει περὶ Θεοῦ ὅτι αὐτὸς, Θεὸς ὣν, ἐστὶν ὁ ποιήσας τὰ πάντα, οὕτε ἐγένετο ὅμοιος αὐτοῦ τις, ἀλλ᾿ εἶς Θεὸς ὁλόσφυρος οὐκ ἐγέννησεν, οὕτ᾿ ἐγεννήθη, ἀλλ᾿ εἶς ἐστιν Θεὸς, καὶ πᾶς ὁ μερίζων αὐτὸν, ἡ ὅμοιον ποιῶν, σωτηρίας οὐκ ἔστιν, ἀλλ᾿ ἀφόρητον, καὶ αἰώνιον κόλασιν. Τοιαῦται τοῦ Μωαμὲδ αἱ νομοθέσίαι, ταῦτα νενομοθέτηκεν τῷ λαῷ Ἰσμαήλ.Quelle: Manuel II Paleologus (Μανουήλ Β΄ Παλαιολόγος, Manouēl B’ Palaiologos) Daten: 14./ 15. Jahrhundert Ort: KonstantinopelTitel der Quelle: Διάλογος μετά τινος Πέρσου (Dialogos meta tinos Persou) = Dialoge mit einem Perser Editionen: K. Förstel, hrsg., Manuel II. Palaiologos: Dialoge mit einem Muslim. Kommentierte Griechisch-Deutsche  Textausgabe (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca, Bd. 1). Würzburg/ Altenberge: Echter Verlag, 1993–1996; E. Trapp, hrsg., Manuel II. Palaiologos, Dialoge mit einem ‘Perser’ (Wiener Byzantinistische Studien 2), Vienna, 1966. Hier Seiten: K. Förstel, hrsg., Manuel II. Palaiologos: Dialoge mit einem Muslim. Kommentierte Griechisch-Deutsche Textausgabe (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca, Bd. 1). Würzburg/ Altenberge: Echter  Verlag, 1995, S. 8; E. Trapp, hrsg., Manuel II. Palaiologos, Dialoge mit einem ‘Perser’ (Wiener Byzantinistische Studien 2), Vienna, 1966, S. 122.Griechischer Text: E. Trapp, hrsg., Manuel II. Palaiologos, Dialoge mit einem ‘Perser’ (Wiener Byzantinistische Studien 2), Vienna, 1966, S. 122, Z. 3–11Ἡμεῖς, ὦ οὗτοι, πιστεύομεν εἰς ἕνα Θεόν [...] Ἡμεῖς, ὦ οὗτοι, πιστεύομεν εἰς ἕνα Θεόν, πατέρα, παντοκράτορα, ποιητὴν οὐρανοῦ καὶ γῆς, ὁρατῶν τε πάντων καὶ ἀοράτων, ἄναρχον, ἀτελεύτητον, ἀσώματον, ἀπαθῆ, ἀναφῆ, ἄψαυστον, ἀψηλάφητον, ἄμορφον, ἀσχημάτιστον, οὐχ ὁλόσφαιρον, ὡς ὑμεῖς, ἀόρατον, ἀθεώρητον, ἀκατανόητον, ἀκατάληπτον, ἄγνωστον, ἄπειρον, ἀόριστον, άπερίγραπτον, ἀπερίληπτον, ἀμετάβατον, άκίνητον, ἄτρεπτον, ἀναλλοίωτον, ἀμέθεκτον, ἀκοινώνητον κατ᾿ οὐσίαν πάσῃ τῇ κτίσει, καὶ συνελόντα εἰπεῖν οὐκ ἐκ τῶν κατ᾿ αὐτόν, ἀλλ᾿ ἐκ τῶν περὶ αὐτῶν, ὡς προείρηται, καὶ ταῖς ἀποφάσεσι μᾶλλον ἣ ταῖς καταφάσεσι γνωριζόμενον, ὡς καὶ Διονυσίῳ δοκεῖ ἀνδρὶ τὴν ἔξω παιδείαν κατ᾿ ἄκρας ἐξησκηκότι καὶ τῷ χορῷ τῶν θεολόγων ἐμπρέψαντι.   Deutsche Übersetzung aus: K. Förstel, hrsg., Manuel II. Palaiologos: Dialoge mit einem Muslim. Kommentierte Griechisch-Deutsche Textausgabe (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca, Bd. 1). Würzburg/ Altenberge: Esther Verlag, 1995, S. 9.Wir, ihr Männer, glauben an einen Gott, der Vater ist, Allberrscher. Erschaffer von Himmel und Erde, von allem Sichtbaren und Unsichtbaren, ohne Anfang, ohne Ende, körperlos, leidenslos, nicht anfaßbar. nicht berührbar, nicht betastbar, gestaltlos, ungeformt, nicht kugelförmig, wie ihr behauptet, nicht sichtbar, nicht anschaubar, unverstehbar, unbegreiflich, unerkennbar, endlos, grenzenlos, nicht eingeschränkt. nicht umfaßt. Ohne Wandel, ohne Bewegung, ohne Wechsel, ohne Änderung, keinen Anteil an sich gebend, keine Wesensgemeinschaft habend mit der gesamten Schöpfung -: um es zusammenzufassen, erkennbar nicht aus dem, was in ihm ist, sondern aus dem, was um ihn ist (das wurde vorhin gesagt?), und eher durch Negationen als durch Affırmationen - das ist die Meinung des Dionysios, eines Mannes, der sich die profane Bildung von Grund auf angeeignet hatte und im Kreis der Theologen hervorglänzte.Quelle: Nicetas Choniates (Νικήτας Χωνιάτης, Nikētas Chōniatēs)  Daten: 11./ 12. Jahrhundert Ort: Konstantinopel Titel der Quelle: Χρονική Διήγησις (Chronikē diēgēsis) = “Geschichtserzählung” Editionen: J.-L. van Dieten, hrsg., Nicetae Choniatae Historia (Corpus Fontium Historiae Byzantinae XI/1-2) Berlin, 1975.Hier Seiten: J.-L. van Dieten, hrsg., Nicetae Choniatae Historia (Corpus Fontium Historiae Byzantinae XI/1-2) Berlin, 1975, S. 213.Griechischer Text: J.-L. van Dieten, hrsg., Nicetae Choniatae Historia (Corpus Fontium Historiae Byzantinae XI/1-2) Berlin, 1975, S. 213, Z. 51–58.Οἷον δὲ καὶ τόδ’ ἔρεξεν ἀνὴρ οὑτοσὶ περὶ τὸ πέρας τῆς αὐτοῦ βιοτῆς. ἔγκειται τῷ κατηχητικῷ πυκτίῳ μεθ’ ἑτέρων ἀφορισμῶν καὶ τὸ ἀνάθεμα τῷ θεῷ τοῦ Μωάμετ, περὶ οὗ λέγει „οὔτε ἐγέννησεν οὔτε ἐγεννήθη“ καὶ ὅτι ὁλόσφυρός ἐστι. τὸν τοιοῦτον τοίνυν ἀναθεματισμὸν ἀπαλεῖψαι τῶν ὅλων κατηχητηρίων βίβλων προέθετο, ἀπ’ αὐτῆς τῆς ἐν τῇ Μεγάλῃ Ἐκκλησίᾳ πυκτίδος ἀρξάμενος. καὶ ἡ πρόφασις ὡς μάλα εὐπρόσωπος·ἔφασκε γὰρ ὡς εἰς σκάνδαλον πρόκειται τῶν μετατιθεμένων Ἀγαρηνῶν εἰς τὴν καθ’ ἡμᾶς θεοσεβῆ πίστιν τὸ βλασφημεῖσθαι ὅλως θεόν.  Deutsche Übersetzung aus: F. Grabler, Die Krone der Komnenen (1118-1180). Abenteurer auf dem Kaiserthron (1180-1195). Die Kreuzfahrer erobern Konstantinopel (1195-1206), Übersetzung, 3 Bd., Graz, 1958.Quelle: Euthymius Zigabenus (Εὐθύμιος Ζιγαβηνός, Euthymios Zigabēnos) Daten: 10./ 11. Jahrhundert Ort: Konstantinopel Titel der Quelle: Πανοπλία δογματική (Panoplia Dogmatikē) = Dogmatische Rüstkammer Editionen: K. Förstel, hrsg., Schriften zum Islam von Arethas und Euthymios Zigabenos und Fragmente der griechischen Koranübersetzung (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca, 7). Griechisch-deutsche Textausgabe von Karl Förstel, Wiesbaden, 2009; J. P. Migne, hrsg. Patrologia Graeca 130, Turnholt (Belgien), 1865, Sp. 1331–1360.   Hier Seiten: K. Förstel, hrsg., Schriften zum Islam von Arethas und Euthymios Zigabenos und Fragmente der griechischen Koranübersetzung (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca, 7). Griechisch-deutsche Textausgabe von Karl Förstel, Wiesbaden, 2009, S. 56; J. P. Migne, hrsg. Patrologia Graeca 130, Turnholt (Belgien), 1865, Sp. 1341.Griechischer Text: K. Förstel, hrsg., Schriften zum Islam von Arethas und Euthymios Zigabenos und Fragmente der griechischen Koranübersetzung (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca, 7). Griechisch-deutsche Textausgabe von Karl Förstel, Wiesbaden, 2009, S. 56, Z. 189–193Ὁλόσφυρον λέγει τὸν Θεὸν, ἤτοι σφαιρικόν. Τοῦτο δὲ τὸ σχῆμα σώματός ἐστι καὶ σῶμα ἐμφαίνει, ὥσπερ δὴ καὶ τὸ{ν} πυκνὸν καὶ πεπιλημένον. Σφαῖρα δὲ ὑλικὴ κατ᾿ αὐτὸν ὁ Θεὸς ὤν οὔτε ἀκούσεται οὔτε ὄψεται· καὶ καταπρανῶς, ὡς ἔτυχεν, ἐνεχθήσεται καὶ ἄτακτα κατακυλισθήσεται.Deutsche Übersetzung aus: K. Förstel, hrsg., Schriften zum Islam von Arethas und Euthymios Zigabenos und Fragmente der griechischen Koranübersetzung (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca, 7). Griechisch-deutsche Textausgabe von Karl Förstel, Wiesbaden, 2009, S. 57     Er sagt, Gott sei undurchdringlich, das heißt kugelförmig. Das ist die Form eines Körpers und bezeichnet einen Körper, ebenso  das Dichte und Feste. Da nach ihm Gott eine materielle Kugel ist, wird er weder hören noch sehen und wird aufs Geratewohl abwärts stürzen und in ungeordneten Bewegungen hinunterrollen.Quelle: Bartholomaios von Edessa (Βαρθολομαῖος Ἐδεσηνός, Bartholomaios Edesēnos)   Daten: 12. Jahrhundert Ort: (?) Titel der Quelle: (Βαρθολομαίου τοῦ Ἐδεσηνοῦ ἔλεγχος Ἀγαρηνοῦ, Bartholomaiou tou Edesēnou elenchos Agarēnou) = Des Bartholomaios von Edessa Widerlegung eines AgarenersEditionen: K. P. Todt, hrsg., Bartholomaios von Edessa. Confutatio Agareni (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca 2), Würzburg 1988; J.-P. Migne, hrsg., Patrologia Graeca, vol. 104, Paris 1896, Sp. 1383–1448. Hier Seiten: K. P. Todt, hrsg., Bartholomaios von Edessa. Confutatio Agareni (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca 2), Würzburg 1988, S. 6 J.-P. Migne, hrsg., Patrologia Graeca, vol. 104, Turnholt (Belgien), 1860, Sp. 1385.Griechischer Text: K. P. Todt, hrsg., Bartholomaios von Edessa. Confutatio Agareni (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca 2), Würzburg 1988, S. 6, Z. 5–22Κἀγὼ ὁ Ἐδεσηνὸς λέγω ὑμῖν· ὁ μὴ γινώσκων λογικὸν υἱὸν καὶ ἀθάνατον θεὸν, οὗτος ἔνοχός ἐστιν εἰς γέεναν τοῦ πυρός, διότι θεὸν ἐλεοῦντα καὶ ἐλεημένοι ὀνομάζεις, καὶ οὗτός ἐστι προφανῶς, ὃν οἱ Ἄρραβες δογματίζετε τὸ ἑωσφόρον ἄστρον Ζέβω, Ἀφροδίτη, Κρόνος καὶ Χαμὰρ λέγετε, αὐτοὺς καλεῖτε θεούς· ἐλέγχω γὰρ ὑμᾶς ἐκ τῆς γραφῆς ὑμῶν, οὗτοι οἱ θεοὶ ὑμῶν κτιστοί εἰσιν καὶ κτῖσμα ἔχουσιν καὶ φθαρτοί εἰσιν, ἔργα χειρῶν ἀνθρώπων καὶ εἴδωλα. καὶ αὐτὸ τὸ ὄνομα, οὖ ἀρχὴ ἐν αὐτοῦ κουρανίου σου, ὅντινα ἐλεοῦντα καὶ ἐλεήμονα μὲν ἀποκαλεῖτε, οὗτοι εἰσιν, οὓς καλεῖτε διὰ τῆς γλώττης ὑμῶν Ἀλἀχ, Σαμέτ, Τζαμέτ, τοῦτ᾿ ἔστιν προφανῶς ὁλόσφυρος καὶ ὁλόβολος, οἷος κρατεῖται καὶ σχῆμα ἔχει. οἱ τὸν τοιοῦτον θεὸν σεβόμενοι οὗτοι εἰσιν οἱ τοῖς ἐκεῖ κολαστηρίοις ἔνοχοι, οἱ δὲ γινώσκοντες καὶ ὁμολογοῦντες τὸ ὄνομα τοῦ λογικοῦ καὶ ζῶντος καὶ ἀθανάτου θεοῦ, οὗτοι εἰσιν οἱ κληρονόνοι τῆς βασιλείας τοῦ θεοῦ καὶ τῆς παραδείσου. Περὶ δὲ ὧν με ἠρώτησας, πάντα ὕστερον σοι ὁμολογήσομαι.Deutsche Übersetzung aus: K. P. Todt, hrsg., Bartholomaios von Edessa. Confutatio Agareni (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca 2), Würzburg 1988, S. 7.Denn ich, der Edessener, sage euch: Wer nicht den vernunftbesitzenden Sohn und unsterblichen Gott anerkennt, der ist der Hölle des Feuers verfallen. Du nennst nämlich Gott den barmherzigen und mitleidigen, und offenbar ist es der, den ihr Araber lehrt der Morgenstern — Zebo, Aphrodite, Kronos und Chamar zählt ihr auf, diese nennt ihr Götter” (denn aus eurer Schrift widerlege ich euch). Diese eure Götter sind geschaffen, sie sind im Zustande des Geschöpfes, vergänglich sind sie, Werke von Menschenhand und Götzenbilder. Und selbst der Name, der am Anfang dieses deines Koranes steht, den ihr den barmherzigen und mitleidigen nennt, meint diese, die ihr in eurer Sprache Alach (Alläh), Samet, Tzamet nennt, dies bedeutet offenbar massiv und kompakt, wie er anzufassen und geformt ist. Die, die den so beschaffenen Gott verehren, die sind den Strafen dort verfallen, die aber, die den Namen des vernunftbesitzenden und lebendigen und unsterblichen Gottes anerkennen und bekennen, die sind die Erben des Reiches Gottes und des Paradieses. Worüber aber du mich (noch) gefragt hast, all dies werde ich dir später erklären.Quelle: Anonym   Daten: 9. Jahrhundert   Ort: unbekannt   Titel der Quelle: (Τάξις γινομένη ἐπὶ τοῖς ἀπὸ Σαρακηνῶν ἐπιστρέφουσι πρὸς τὴν καθαρὰν καὶ ἀληθῆ πίστιν ἡμῶν τῶν Χριστιανῶν, Taxis ginomenē epi tois apo Sarakēnōn epistrephousi pros tēn katharan kai alēthē pistin hēmōn tōn christianōn) = Abschwörungsritual, Abschwördungsformel, Abjuratio   Editionen: É. Montet, hrsg., Un rituel d’abjuration des Musulmans dans l’église grecque, in Revue de l'histoire des religions 53 (1906), S. 145–163; J.-P. Migne, hrsg., Patrologia Graeca, Bd. 140, Paris 1887, Sp. 124–136.   Hier Seiten: É. Montet, hrsg., Un rituel d’abjuration des Musulmans dans l’église grecque, in Revue de l’histoire des religions 53 (1906), S. 155; J.-P. Migne, hrsg., Patrologia Graeca, Bd. 140, Paris 1887, Sp. 133–134.Griechischer Text: É. Montet, hrsg., Un rituel d’abjuration des Musulmans dans l’église grecque, in Revue de l'histoire des religions 53 (1906), S. 155, Z. 22–26Καὶ ἐπὶ πᾶσι τούτοις ἀναθεματίζω τὸν θεὸν τοῦ Μωάμεδ περὶ οὗ λέγει ὅτι «αὐτός ἐστι θεός εἷς θεὸς ὁλόσφυρος, οὐκ ἐγέννησεν οὐδὲ ἐγεννήθη οὐδὲ ἐγένετο ὅμοιος αὐτῷ τις.»    dazu TUK von MM mit bezug zu Vogelwunder (Link)</summary>
            <msItem>
              <title>Niketas von Byzanz, Ἀνατροπὴ τοῦ Κορανίου ("Widerlegung des Koran"), Conf. I, lin. 81–92, Conf. XVIII, lin. 143–152</title>
              <author/>
              <textLang mainLang="ell">Griechisch</textLang>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc> </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate calendar="gregorian">900-1000</origDate>
              <origPlace/>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <source>
                  <p>The editors and contributions to Corpus Coranicum.</p>
                </source>
              </recordHist>
            </adminInfo>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl type="edition"/>
              <bibl type="literatur">Arethas &amp;amp;amp; Zigave&amp;amp;#x304;nos, Euthymios: Schriften zum Islam von Arethas und Euthymios Zigabenos und Fragmente der griechischen Koranu&amp;amp;#x308;bersetzung (K. Fo&amp;amp;#x308;rstel, Hrsg.). Harrassowitz, Wiesbaden 2009.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Devresse, Robert (Hrsg.): Codices Vaticani Graeci. Vol. III (Codd. 604-866). Bibliotheca vaticana, Romae 1950.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">F&amp;amp;#xF6;rstel, Karl (Hrsg.): Niketas von Byzanz, Schriften zum Islam, I. Griechisch-deutsche Textausgabe. Echter/Oros, Altenberge 2000.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">H&amp;amp;#xF8;gel, Christian: &amp;amp;#x201E;An early anonymous Greek translation of the Qur&amp;amp;#x2019;&amp;amp;#x101;n. The fragments from Niketas Byzantios&amp;amp;#x2019; Refutatio and the anonymous Abjuratio&amp;amp;#x201C;. In: Collect. christ. orient. 7 (2010), S. 65&amp;amp;#x2013;119.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Holtzman, Livnat: &amp;amp;#x201E;Anthropomorphism&amp;amp;#x201C;. Encyclopaedia of Islam 3:.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Lampe, G.H.W. (Hrsg.): A Patristic Lexicon. Claredon Press, Oxford .</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Mai, Angelo (Hrsg.): Nova Patrum Bibliotheca 4 (Nicetas of Byzantium). Typis Sacri Consilii Propagando Christiano Nomini, Rom 1848.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Manuel II. Palaiologos: Dialoge mit einem &amp;amp;#x201E;Perser&amp;amp;#x201C; (E. Trapp, Hrsg.). Verlag der &amp;amp;#xD6;sterreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, Wien 1966.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Migne, J.P. (Hrsg.): Patrologia Graeca 104 (Contra Mohamed). Garnier Fr&amp;amp;#xE8;res, Paris 1896.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Migne, J.P. (Hrsg.): Patrologia Graeca 105 (Nicetas of Byzantium). Turnholt 1862.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Montet: &amp;amp;#x201E;Un rituel d&amp;amp;#x2019;abjuration des musulmans dans l&amp;amp;#x2019;&amp;amp;#xE9;glise grecque&amp;amp;#x201C;. In: Revue de l&amp;amp;#x2019;histoire des religions 53 (1906), S. 145&amp;amp;#x2013;63.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Nicetas Byzantinus: &amp;amp;#x201E;Vat.gr.681 (Refutatio Mohamedis)&amp;amp;#x201C;. Manuscript - Vat.gr.681.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Rigo, Antonio: &amp;amp;#x201E;Niceta Byzantios, la sua opera e il monaco Evodio&amp;amp;#x201C;. In: G. Fiaccadori (Hrsg.), Scritti in onore di Giovanni Pugliese Carratelli. Vivarium, Neapel 2006,</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Sahas, Daniel: &amp;amp;#x201E;Holosphyros&amp;quot;? A Byzantine Perception of &amp;quot;The Muhammad&amp;amp;#x201C;. In: Y.Y. Haddad &amp;amp;amp; W.Z. Haddad, (Hrsg.), Christian-Muslim Encounters. University Press of Florida, Gainsville 1995, S. 109&amp;amp;#x2013;125.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Simelidis, Christos: &amp;amp;#x201E;The Byzantine Understanding of the Qur&amp;amp;#x55A;anic Term al-&amp;amp;#x1E62;amad and the Greek Translation of the Qur&amp;amp;#x55A;an&amp;amp;#x201C;. In: Speculum 86 (2011), S. 887&amp;amp;#x2013;913.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Trapp, E.: &amp;amp;#x201E;Gab es eine byzantinische Koran&amp;amp;#xFC;bersetzung?&amp;amp;#x201C; In: Diptycha Hetaireias Byzantin&amp;amp;#x14D;n kai Metabyzantin&amp;amp;#x14D;n Melet&amp;amp;#x14D;n 2 (1980), S. 7&amp;amp;#x2013;17.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Ulbricht, Manolis: &amp;amp;#x201E;Der Islam-Diskurs bei Niketas von Byzanz: Themen und Argumentation in seinem Hauptwerk &amp;amp;#x201A;Widerlegung des Korans&amp;amp;#x2018; (&amp;amp;#x1FBF;A&amp;amp;#x3BD;&amp;amp;#x3B1;&amp;amp;#x3C4;&amp;amp;#x3C1;&amp;amp;#x3BF;&amp;amp;#x3C0;&amp;amp;#x1F74; &amp;amp;#x3C4;&amp;amp;#x3BF;&amp;amp;#x1FE6; &amp;amp;#x39A;&amp;amp;#x3BF;&amp;amp;#x3C1;&amp;amp;#x3B1;&amp;amp;#x3BD;&amp;amp;#x3AF;&amp;amp;#x3BF;&amp;amp;#x3C5;)&amp;amp;#x201C;. In: Byzantinische Zeitschrift 114 (2021), S. 1351&amp;amp;#x2013;1394.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Created as part of
            <name type="project">Corpus Coranicum Project</name>
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantsreader">
          <bibl>Variants Readers</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantssource">
          <bibl>Variants Sources</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="tuk.cat">
          <bibl>TUK Categories</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="geoname">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="https://www.geonames.org/">Geonames</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="local">
          <bibl>'Sigle' is a unique id assigned by Michael Marx to a specific reader in the reading
                variants.
            </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change type="TEI_record_creater">
        <persName role="dtc">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription" xml:lang="ell">
        <p>S. 44 (Conf. I, lin. 81–92)Εἰς μὲν θεολογίαν ταύτην ἔρρηξε τὴν ἄθεον φωνήν, ὅτι σφαιρικόν ἐστι τὸ θεῖον, μᾶλλον δέ, ὡς αὐτὸς εἶπεν, ὁλόσφαιρός ἐστιν ὁ Θεὸς, σῶμα πάντως αὐτὸν οἰόμενος· οὐ γὰρ ἂν ἄλλως τὸ τῆς σφαίρας ἐδέχετο σχῆμα. Σφαῖρα δὲ ὑλικὴ κατ᾽ αὐτὸν τυγχάνων οὔτε ἀκούσεται οὔτε ὄψεται νοητῶς δηλονότι οὔτε ἐνεργήσει πάλιν, εἴ που τύχοι παρ᾽ ἄλλου κινηθείς καὶ μάλιστα κατὰ πρανοῦς ἀλογίστως φέρεσθαι. Ἱλάσθητι ἡμῖν, ὁ Θεός, τὰ αὐτοῦ λέγουσιν, εἰ καὶ κατ᾽ αὐτοῦ. Εἰ δὲ δὴ αὐτὸν τὸν οὐρανὸν τὸν Θεὸν λέγει, ὡς πολλοὶ τῶν Ἑλλήνων ἐλήρησαν, καὶ οὕτως ἀληθεύσει ὁ λόγος δαιμονιώδη αὐτὸν εἰρηκὼς εἶναι. Εἰς δὲ φυσιολογίαν (48v) ἢ οὐδὲν φάναι ἠπίστατο ἤ, εἰ καὶ προκύψαι εἰς τοῦτο ἐτόλμησεν, λέγει, ὅτι ἐκ βδέλλης ὁ ἄνθρωπος γίνεται καὶ ὁ ἥλιος εἰς θερμὸν ὕδωρ καταβαπτίζεται πρὸς ἑσπέραν φερόμενος.S. 116–118 (Conf. XVIII, lin. 143–152)Τὸ ἑκατοστὸν δέκατον μυθάριον Εἰς τὸν Βουλαάπ, ὃν ἄδικον γεγονότα ἐν πυρὶ καίεσθαι ὁμολογεῖ τῆς αὐτοῦ γυναικὸς ὑποκαιούσης κάμινον. Τὸ ἑκατοστὸν ἑνδέκατον μυθάριον ἔχει οὕτως· “Εἰπέ, αὐτός ἐστι Θεὸς εἷς, Θεὸς ὁλόσφυρος. Οὐκ ἐγέννησεν οὐδὲ ἐγεννήθη, οὐδὲ ἐγένετο ὅμοιος αὐτῷ.” Εἰ μὴ τὸ σχῆμα τῆς σφαίρας δηλοῖ τὸ ὁλόσφυρον, ἀλλά γε τὸ πυκνὸν καὶ πεπιλημένον, ὅπερ καὶ αὐτὸ τοῦ σώματος ἴδιον. Τὸ δωδέκατον καὶ ἑκατοστὸν ἐπιγέγραπται Εἰς τὸ φεύξομαι, ἔστι δὲ γοητικὴ ἐπιφώνησις· ἔχει γὰρ οὕτως· “Εἰπέ, φεύξομαι εἰς τὸν Κύριον τοῦ διαφαύσματος ἐκ κακοῦ, τοῦ ἔπλασε, καὶ ἐκ κακοῦ τῆς ἀστροτοξίας, ὅταν ἐκτείνηται, καὶ ἐκ κακοῦ ἐμπτυσμάτων εἰς τοὺς κόμβους καὶ ἐκ κακοῦ φθόνου φθονοῦντος.”</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="deu">
        <p>Deutsche Übersetzung aus: K. Förstel, hrsg., Nicetas von Byzanz: Schriften zum Islam (Corpus Islamo-Christianum, Series Graeca, 5), Bd. 1, Griechisch-deutsche Textausgabe von Karl Förstel, Würzburg/Altenberge, 2000 S. 45, 117–119In In der Theologie tat er diese gottlose Äußerung, daß die Gottheit kugelförmig ist, besser, wie er selbst sagte, daß Gott eine Vollkugel ist, indem er ihn ganz und gar für einen Körper hielt; denn anders hätte er die Kugelgestalt nicht annehmen können. Wenn Gott nach ihm eine stoffliche Kugel ist, wird er weder hören noch sehen, nämlich mit dem geistigen Auge, noch. ferner tätig werden, wenn er etwa, von einem anderen Körper angestoßen, sich hauptsächlich nach unten sinnlos [85] bewegt, Verzeih' uns, Gott, daß wir seine Ansichten anführen, wenn auch nur gegen ihn! Wenn er den Himmel selbst Gott’nennt, wie viele Heiden fabuliert haben, so dürfe auch dann unser Urteil zutreffend sein, das ihn vom Dämon besessen nannte. In der Naturphilosophie wußte er entweder nichts zu sagen, oder er sagt, wenn er auf dieses Gebiet auch nur herauszulugen wagte, daß der [90] Mensch aus einem Blutegel entsteht und daß die Sonne, wenn sie sich gegen Westen bewegt, in warmes Wasser untertaucht.der Theologie tat er diese gottlose Äußerung, daß die Gottheit kugelförmig ist, besser, wie er selbst sagte, daß Gott eine Vollkugel istDie hundertzehnte Fabel heißt ‘Auf Abu Lahab’. Er versichert, daß dieser, weil er sich ungerecht gezeigt hatte, im Feuer brenne, wobei seine Frau den Ofen anheize, Die hundertelfte Fabel lautet so: „Sprich, er ist Gott, ein Einziger, Gott, der Undurchdringliche. Er hat nicht gezeugt worden, und nieman ist ihm ebenbürtig“. Wenn das Wort ‚undurchdringlich‘ auch nicht die Kugelgestalt bezeichnet, so doch das Dichte und Feste, das seinerseits eine Eigenschaft des Körpers ist. Die hundertzwölfte ist überschrieben ‘Auf die Zuflucht’. Sie ist ein Ausruf der Klage; sie lautet so: „Sprich: Ich will Zuflucht suchen beim Herrn des Frühlichts vor dem Unheil von dem, was er erschaffen hat, vor dem Unheil der Sternschnuppe, wenn sie sich ausbreitet, vor dem Unheil des Spuckens auf die Knoten und vor dem Unheil des Neids eines Neidischen“.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
        <p/>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
