<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tuk_doi">
  <!--add the DOI here!-->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>De opificio mundi 3:13-14</title>
        <title/>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <date calendar="#Gregorian">19-12-2024</date>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
        <idno type="tuk_DOI">askxxx</idno>
        <!--the DOI could be repeated here-->
        <idno type="instID">askxxx</idno>
        <!--CCint.institutional ID-->
        <idno type="CCTUKID"/>
        <!--CCint.msID-->
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:id="tuk_1114" xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>Corpus Coranicum</repository>
            <idno>1114</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
	Der Koran teilt mit der jüdischen und christlichen Tradition die Vorstellung, dass Gott die Welt in sechs Tagen erschaffen habe. Dieser Gedanke findet sich nicht nur in Genesis und Exodus (vgl. TUK_1112), sondern, wie der vorliegende Text und andere (TUK_1113, TUK_1115) exemplarisch zeigen, auch in der späteren Literatur.
</summary>
            <msItem>
              <title>De opificio mundi 3:13-14</title>
              <author>Philo von Alexandria (ca. 20/10 v. Chr. - 40/50 n.Chr.)</author>
              <textLang mainLang="ell">Griechisch</textLang>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc> </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate calendar="gregorian">vor 50 n. Chr.</origDate>
              <origPlace>Alexandria</origPlace>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <source>
                  <p>The editors and contributions to Corpus Coranicum.</p>
                </source>
              </recordHist>
            </adminInfo>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl type="edition">Philonis Alexandrini Opera quae supersunt ediderunt Leopoldus Cohn et Paulus Wendland Vol. I, p. 6-60 Berolini 1896.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Created as part of
            <name type="project">Corpus Coranicum Project</name>
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantsreader">
          <bibl>Variants Readers</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantssource">
          <bibl>Variants Sources</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="tuk.cat">
          <bibl>TUK Categories</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="geoname">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="https://www.geonames.org/">Geonames</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="local">
          <bibl>'Sigle' is a unique id assigned by Michael Marx to a specific reader in the reading
                variants.
            </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change type="TEI_record_creater">
        <persName role="dtc">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
      </change>
      <change type="transliteration">
        <persName key="" role="trc">Veronika Roth</persName>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription" xml:lang="ell">
        <p>
13 ἓξ δὲ ἡμέραις δημιουργηθῆναι φησιλέγω τὸν κόσμον, οὐκ ἐπειδὴ προσεδεῖτοπροσδέομαι χρόνων μήκους ὁ ποιῶν ἅμα γὰρ πάντα δρᾶν εἰκὸς θεόν, οὐ προστάττοντα μόνον ἀλλὰ καὶ διανοούμενον ἀλλ᾽ ἐπειδὴ τοῖς γινομένοισγίνομαι ἔδει τάξεως. τάξει δὲ ἀριθμὸς οἰκεῖον, ἀριθμῶν δὲ φύσεως νόμοις γεννητικώτατος ὁ ἕξ· τῶν τε γὰρ ἀπὸ μονάδος πρῶτος τέλειόστέλεος ἐστιν ἰσούμενος τοῖς ἑαυτοῦ μέρεσι καὶ συμπληρούμενος ἐξ αὐτῶν, ἡμίσους μὲν τριάδος, τρίτου δὲ δυάδος, ἕκτου δὲ μονάδος, καὶ ὡς ἔπος εἰπεῖνλέγω ἄρρηνἄρρην τε καὶ θῆλυς εἶναι πέφυκε κἀκκαί τῆς ἑκατέρου δυνάμεως ἥρμοσται· ἄρρενἄρρην μὲν γὰρ ἐν τοῖς οὖσι τὸ περιττόν, τὸ δ᾽ ἄρτιον θῆλυ· περιττῶν μὲν οὖν ἀριθμῶν ἀρχὴ τριάς, δυὰς δ᾽ ἀρτίων, ἡ δ᾽ ἀμφοῖν δύναμις ἑξάς. 14 ἔδει γὰρ τὸν κόσμον τελειότατοντέλεος μὲν ὄντα τῶν γεγονότωνγίνομαι κατ᾽ ἀριθμὸν τέλειοντέλεος παγῆναι τὸν ἕξ, ἐν ἑαυτῷ δ᾽ ἔχειν μέλλοντα τὰς ἐκ συνδυασμοῦ γενέσεις πρὸς μικτὸν ἀριθμὸν τὸν πρῶτον ἀρτιοπέριττον τυπωθῆναι, περιέξοντα καὶ τὴν τοῦ σπείροντος ἄρρενοσἄρρην καὶ τὴν τοῦ ὑποδεχομένου τὰς γονὰς θήλεος ἰδέαν.
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="deu">
        <p>13 (3.) In sechs Tagen, sagt er, ist die Welt geschaffen worden, nicht etwa weil der Schöpfer einen Zeitraum dazu nötig hatte
— denn es ist selbstverständlich, dass Gott alles auf einmal bewirkt, nicht nur durch seinen Befehl, sondern schon durch sein Denken —, sondern weil für die Entstehung der Dinge eine bestimmte Ordnung nötig war. Zur Ordnung aber gehört
die Zahl, und von den Zahlen ist nach den Gesetzen der Natur die für die Schöpfung passendste die Sechs. Wenn man nämlich von der Eins an zählt, ist sie die erste vollkommene Zahl, da sie ihren Teilen gleich und aus ihnen zusammengesetzt ist, nämlich aus der Drei als der Hälfte, der Zwei als dem 3. Teil und der Eins als dem 6. Teil; zugleich ist sie, so zu sagen, sowohl männlich als weiblich und durch die Kraft der Vermischung beider Prinzipien zusammengesetzt; männlich ist nämlich in der Natur das Ungerade, das Gerade dagegen weiblich; von den ungeraden Zahlen ist nun die erste die 3, von den geraden die 2, und das Produkt beider ist die 6. 14 Denn es musste die Welt als das vollkommenste der gewordenen Dinge nach einer vollkommenen Zahl, der Sechs, geschaffen werden, und da sie die aus Paarung entstehenden Geschöpfe enthalten sollte, so musste sie auch selbst nach einer gemischten Zahl, der ersten geraden-ungeraden, gebildet werden, weil sie sowohl die Idee des den Samen spendenden Männlichen als die Idee des den Samen empfangenden Weiblichen umfassen sollte.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
        <p>
13 III. And he [Moses] says that the world was made in six days, not because the Creator stood in need of a length of time (for it is natural that God should do everything at once, not merely by uttering a command, but by even thinking of it); but because the things created required arrangement; and number is akin to arrangement; and, of all numbers, six is, by the laws of nature, the most productive: for of all the numbers, from the unit upwards, it is the first perfect one, being made equal to its parts, and being made complete by them; the number three being half of it, and the number two a third of it, and the unit a sixth of it, and, so to say, it is formed so as to be both male and female, and is made up of the power of both natures; for in existing things the odd number is the male, and the even number is the female; accordingly, of odd numbers the first is the number three, and of even numbers the first is two, and the two numbers multiplied together make six. 14 It was fitting therefore, that the world, being the most perfect of created things, should be made according to the perfect number, namely, six: and, as it was to have in it the causes of both, which arise from combination, that it should be formed according to a mixed number, the first combination of odd and even numbers, since it was to embrace the character both of the male who sows the seed, and of the female who receives it.
</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
