<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tuk_doi">
  <!--add the DOI here!-->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hohes Lied Rabba, Parascha 1</title>
        <title/>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <date calendar="#Gregorian">19-12-2024</date>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
        <idno type="tuk_DOI">askxxx</idno>
        <!--the DOI could be repeated here-->
        <idno type="instID">askxxx</idno>
        <!--CCint.institutional ID-->
        <idno type="CCTUKID"/>
        <!--CCint.msID-->
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:id="tuk_1086" xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>Corpus Coranicum</repository>
            <idno>1086</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
	1 Könige 5:9-14 (TUK_0324) erwähnt, dass Gott Salomon besondere Weisheit verliehen habe. Die hier zitierte Stelle aus Hld Rabba zeigt, dass die Assoziation Salomos mit Weisheit auch in den späteren Traditionen sehr geläufig ist,  vgl. auch Mt 12:42 (TUK_1084), Lk 11:31, Sirach 47:14-17, Flavius Josephus: Jüdische Altertümer (TUK_1085), Babylonischer Talmud, Erubim 21b und Berakot 56b.

	Zu Datierung und Textgeschichte siehe Stemberger 2011, S. 349-350.
</summary>
            <msItem>
              <title>Hohes Lied Rabba, Parascha 1</title>
              <author/>
              <textLang mainLang="heb">Hebräisch</textLang>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc> </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate calendar="gregorian">2. Hälfte des 6. Jh.</origDate>
              <origPlace/>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <source>
                  <p>The editors and contributions to Corpus Coranicum.</p>
                </source>
              </recordHist>
            </adminInfo>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl type="edition"/>
            </listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Created as part of
            <name type="project">Corpus Coranicum Project</name>
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantsreader">
          <bibl>Variants Readers</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantssource">
          <bibl>Variants Sources</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="tuk.cat">
          <bibl>TUK Categories</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="geoname">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="https://www.geonames.org/">Geonames</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="local">
          <bibl>'Sigle' is a unique id assigned by Michael Marx to a specific reader in the reading
                variants.
            </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change type="TEI_record_creater">
        <persName role="dtc">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
      </change>
      <change type="transliteration">
        <persName key="" role="trc">Veronika Roth</persName>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription" xml:lang="heb">
        <p>
	ד"א שיר השירים זה שאמר הכתוב (משלי טז) לב חכם ישכיל פיהו לבו של חכם מלא חכמה מי ישכיל עליו ומי מחכים עליו פיהו, פומיה מחכים עלוי, פומיה מורה עלוי (שם /משלי ט"ז/) ועל שפתיו יוסיף לקח מתוך שהוא מוציא דברי תורה מלבו מוסיף על לקחה של תורה, משלו משל לה"ד לחבית שהיא מלאה אבנים טובות ומרגליות ומוקפת צמיד פתיל והיא נתונה בזוית אחת ואין אדם יודע מה בתוכה בא אחד ופנה אותה וידעו הכל מה בתוכה, כך לבו של שלמה היה מלא חכמה ולא היה יודע אדם מה בתוכה כיון ששרתה עליו רוח הקודש ואמר ג' ספרים ידעו הכל חכמתו
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="deu">
        <p>Oder: Lied der Lieder. Das sagt auch die Schrift Prov. 16,23: "Des Weisen Herz macht seinen Mund beredt und auf seinen Lippen mehrt es Lehre" d.i. das Herz des Weisen ist voll Weisheit und wer macht die Weisheit kund? Sein Mund, und dadurch, dass er die Worte der Thora aus seinem Herzen hervorbringt, verbreitet und vermehrt er die Lehre (Unterweisung) der Thora. Es verhält sich damit wie mit einem Fasse, welches voll Edelsteinen und Perlen ist und verschlossen und in einen Winkel geworfen liegt und niemand seinen Inhalt kennt. Da kommt ein Mensch, holt es hervor und leert es aus, und nun erkennen alle, was darin ist. So war auch Salomos Herz voll Weisheit, aber niemand wusste es. Als aber der heilige Geist auf ihm ruhte, und er die drei Bücher abfasste, da erkannten alle seine Weisheit.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
        <p>
	7. Another explanation: The Song of Songs: this bears out what the text says, The heart of the wise teacheth his mouth (Spr 16:23). If the heart of the wise man is full of wisdom, who draws attention to him and who shows his wisdom? 'His mouth.' His mouth makes him wise. His mouth shows what he is. 'And addeth learning to his lips' (Spr. 16:23). Through the act of bringing forth words of Torah from his heart, he adds to learning in the Torah. They drew a comparison to illustrate this, to a cask which was full of precious stones and pearls, but which had a tight fitting cover and was put away in a corner, so that no one knew what was in it, until someone came and emptied it and then everyone knew what was in it. So the heart of Salomon was full of wisdom but no one knew what was in it, but when the holy spirit rested on him and he composed three books, all knew his wisdom.
</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
