<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tuk_doi">
  <!--add the DOI here!-->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Leviticus 19:16</title>
        <title/>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <date calendar="#Gregorian">19-12-2024</date>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
        <idno type="tuk_DOI">askxxx</idno>
        <!--the DOI could be repeated here-->
        <idno type="instID">askxxx</idno>
        <!--CCint.institutional ID-->
        <idno type="CCTUKID"/>
        <!--CCint.msID-->
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:id="tuk_811" xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>Corpus Coranicum</repository>
            <idno>811</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
	Die Koranstelle spricht vom "Essen des Fleisches seines Bruders" im Kontext von Anweisungen gegen üble Nachrede, Verleumdung etc. Dieser Ausdruck erinnert, wie bereits von Ahrens 1930: p. 43 bemerkt, an den syrischen Begriff ekal qarṣē 'die Stücke (Brot, Fleisch jemandes) essen' (auch im Singular). In der Peschitta findet er sich noch etwa in Daniel 3:8 und Matthäus 12:10. Der Teufel, als 'Ankläger, Verleumder, diabolos' wird auch gerne als ākel qarṣā bezeichnet. Der Begriff findet sich auch sonst aramäisch, etwa im Mandäischen und Jüdisch-Babylonisch-Aramäischen (Sokoloff 2002: p. 41). Am frühesten belegt ist der Ausdruck im Akkadischen: karṣē akālu. Gleich, ob ein ähnlicher Ausdruck auch im Arabischen geläufig war oder nicht, ist die parallele Wortwahl in ähnlichem Kontext auffällig. Die syrische Version von Leviticus wurde hier aufgrund der sprachlichen Nähe verwendet. Vgl. dazu auch Krebernick 2008: p. 265.
</summary>
            <msItem>
              <title>Leviticus 19:16</title>
              <author/>
              <textLang mainLang="syc">Syrisch</textLang>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc> </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate calendar="gregorian">vor 4. Jh. v. Chr. (Endredaktion des Pentateuchs)</origDate>
              <origPlace>Palästina</origPlace>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <source>
                  <p>The editors and contributions to Corpus Coranicum.</p>
                </source>
              </recordHist>
            </adminInfo>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl type="edition">David J. Lane (Hg.), The Old Testament in Syriac according to the Peshitta Version, Part I, fasc. 2: Leviticus; Numbers; Deuteronomy. E.J. Brill, Leiden 1991, S. 48-51.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Ahrens, Karl: &amp;#x201E;Christliches im Qoran. Eine Nachlese&amp;#x201C;. In: Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morgenl&amp;#xE4;ndischen Gesellschaft 84 (1930), S. 15&amp;#x2013;68, 148&amp;#x2013;190.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Krebernick, Manfred: &amp;#x201E;Von Gindibu bis Mu&amp;#x1E25;ammad&amp;#x201C;. In: Otto Jastrow, Shabo Talay, &amp;amp; H. Hafenrichter (Hrsg.), Studien zur Semitistik und Arabistik. Festschrift f&amp;#xFC;r Hartmut Bobzin zum 60. Geburtstag. Harrassowitz, Wiesbaden 2008, S. 247&amp;#x2013;280.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Sokoloff, Michael: A dictionary of Jewish Babylonian Aramaic of the Talmudic and Geonic periods. Bar Ilan Univ. Press, Ramat-Gan 2002.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Created as part of
            <name type="project">Corpus Coranicum Project</name>
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantsreader">
          <bibl>Variants Readers</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantssource">
          <bibl>Variants Sources</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="tuk.cat">
          <bibl>TUK Categories</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="geoname">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="https://www.geonames.org/">Geonames</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="local">
          <bibl>'Sigle' is a unique id assigned by Michael Marx to a specific reader in the reading
                variants.
            </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change type="TEI_record_creater">
        <persName role="dtc">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
      </change>
      <change type="transliteration">
        <persName key="" role="trc">David Kiltz</persName>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription" xml:lang="syc">
        <p>1 ܘܡܠܠ ܡܪܝܐ ܥܡ ܡܘܫܐ ܘܐܡܪ ܠܗ.2 ܡܠܠ ܥܡ ܟܠܗ̇ ܟܢܘܫܬܐ ܕܒܢ̈ܝ ܐܝܣܪܝܠ ܘܐܡܪ ܠܗܘܢ. ܗܘܘ ܩܕܝܫ̈ܝܢ ܡܛܠ ܕܩܕܝܫ ܐܢܐ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ ܐܠܗܟܘܢ.3 ܓܒܪ ܡܢ ܐܒܘܗܝ ܘܡܢ ܐܡܗ ܕܚܠܘ. ܘܛܪܘ ܦܘܩ̈ܕܢܝ. ܡܛܠ ܕܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ ܐܠܗܟܘܢ.4 ܠܐ ܬܬܦܢܘܢ ܒܬܪ ܫܐ̈ܕܐ. ܘܐ̈ܠܗܐ ܕܢܣܟܬܐ ܠܐ ܬܥܒܕܘܢ ܠܟܘܢ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ ܐܠܗܟܘܢ.5 ܘܐܢ ܕܒ̇ܚܝܢ ܐܢܬܘܢ ܕܒܚ̈ܐ ܫ̈ܠܡܐ ܠܡܪܝܐ. ܡܩ̈ܒܠܐ ܕܒܚܘ.6 ܘܒܝܘܡܐ ܕܡܬܕܒܚܝܢ ܢܬܐܟܠܘܢ. †ܘܠܝܘܡܐ† ܐܚܪܢܐ ܢܬܐܟܠܘܢ. ܘܡܕܡ ܕܝ̇ܬܪ ܠܝܘܡܐ ܕܬܠܬܐ ܒܢܘܪܐ ܢܐܩܕ ܘܠܐ ܢܬܐܟܠ.7 ܘܐܢ ܡܬܐܟܠܘ ܢܬܐܟܠ ܒܝܘܡܐ ܕܬܠܬܐ. ܡܣܠܝ ܗܘ ܘܠܐ ܢܬܩܒܠ.8 ܘܡ̇ܢ ܕܐ̇ܟܠ ܡܢܗ ܚܛܗܐ ܢܩܒܠ. ܡܛܠ ܕܩܘܕܫܗ ܕܡܪܝܐ ܛܘܫ. ܘܬܐܒܕ ܢܦܫܐ ܗ̇ܝ ܡܢ ܥܡܗ̇.9 ܘܡܐ ܕܚ̇ܨܕܝܢ ܐܢܬܘܢ ܚܨܕܐ ܕܐܪܥܟܘܢ. ܠܐ ܬܓܡܪܘܢ ܣܦܖ̈ܐ ܕܚܩ̈ܠܬܟܘܢ ܠܡܚܨܕ. ܘܠܩܛܐ ܕܚܨܕܟܘܢ ܠܐ ܬܠܩܛܘܢ.10 ܘܟܖ̈ܡܝܟܘܢ ܠܐ ܬܒܥܪܘܢ. ܘܢܬܪܐ ܕܙܝܬ̈ܝܟܘܢ ܠܐ ܬܠܩܛܘܢ. ܐܠܐ ܫܒܘܩܘ ܐܢܘܢ ܠܡܣ̈ܟܢܐ ܘܠܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܡܬܦܢܝܢ ܠܘܬܝ. ܡܛܠ ܕܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ ܐܠܗܟܘܢ.11 ܠܐ ܬܓܢܒܘܢ. ܠܐ ܬܟܕܒܘܢ. ܠܐ ܬܕܓܠܘܢ ܐܢܫ ܒܚܒܪܗ.12 ܠܐ ܬܐܡܘܢ ܒܫܡܝ ܒܟܕܒܘܬܐ. ܘܬܛܘܫܘܢ ܫܡܗ ܕܐܠܗܟܘܢ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ.13 ܠܐ ܬܛܠܘܡ ܠܚܒܪܟ. ܘܠܐ ܬܕܒܪܝܘܗܝ ܒܩܛܝܪܐ. ܠܐ ܢܒܘܬ ܐܓܪܐ ܕܐܓܝܪܐ ܠܘܬܟ ܥܕܡܐ ܠܨܦܪܐ܀14 ܠܐ ܬܨܚܐ ܠܚܪܫܐ. ܘܩܕܡ ܥܘܝܪܐ ܠܐ ܬܣܝܡ ܬܘܩܠܬܐ. ܐܠܐ ܕܚܠ ܡܢ ܐܠܗܟ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ.15 ܠܐ ܬܥܒܕܘܢ ܥܘܠܐ ܒܕܝܢܐ. ܘܠܐ ܬܣܒ ܒܐ̈ܦܝ ܡܣܟܢܐ. ܘܐܦ ܠܐ ܒܐ̈ܦܝ ܪܒܐ. ܐܠܐ ܒܙܕܝܩܘܬܐ ܕܘܢ ܚܒܪܟ.16 ܠܐ ܬܐܟܘܠ ܩܖ̈ܨܐ ܕܥܡܟ. ܘܠܐ ܬܩܘܡ ܥܠ ܕܡܐ ܕܚܒܪܟ܂ ܡܛܠ ܕܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ.17 ܠܐ ܬܣܢܐ ܠܐܚܘܟ ܒܠܒܢ. ܐܠܐ ܡܟܣܘ ܐܟܣܝܗܝ ܠܚܒܪܟ. ܕܠܐ ܡܛܠܬܗ ܬܩܒܠ ܚܛܗܐ.18 ܠܐ ܬܛܪ ܒܥܠܕܒܒܘܬܐ ܠܒܢ̈ܝ ܥܡܟ. ܐܠܐ ܪܚܡ ܠܚܒܪܟ ܐܝܟ ܢܦܫܟ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ.19 ܛܪܘ ܦܘܩ̈ܕܢܝ. ܒܥܝܖ̈ܟܘܢ ܠܐ ܬܪܟܒܘܢ ܚܠܛܐ. ܘܚܩ̈ܠܬܟܘܢ ܠܐ ܬܙܪܥܘܢ ܚܠܛܐ. ܘܡܖ̈ܛܘܛܐ ܕܚܠܛܐ ܕܦܬܝܟܝܢ ܠܐ ܬܠܒܫܘܢ.20 ܘܓܒܪܐ ܕܢܕܡܟ ܥܡ ܐܢܬܬܐ ܡܕܡܟܐ ܕܙܪܥܐ. ܘܐܡܬܗ ܗܝ ܙܒܝܢܐ ܠܗ ܠܓܒܪܐ. ܘܡܬܦܪܩܘ ܠܐ ܐܬܦܪܩܬ. ܘܚܐܪܘܬܐ ܠܐ ܐܬܝܗܒܬ ܠܗ̇. ܫ̈ܐܘܠܐ ܢܗܘܘܢ ܥܠܝܗܘܢ ܘܠܐ ܢܬܩܛܠܘܢ. ܡܛܠ ܕܠܐ ܗܘܬ ܡܚܪܪܐ.21 ܘܢܝܬܐ †ܩܘܪܒܢܗ† ܠܡܪܝܐ. ܠܬܪܥܐ ܕܡܫܟܢ ܙܒܢܐ. ܕܟܪܐ ܕܚܛܗܐ.22 ܘܢܚܣܐ ܥܠܘܗܝ. ܟܗܢܐ ܒܕܟܪܐ ܕܚܛܗܐ ܩܕܡ ܡܪܝܐ. ܥܠ ܚܛܗܐ ܕܚܛܐ. ܘܢܫܬܒܩ ܠܗ ܚܛܗܐ ܕܚܛܐ. 23 ܘܡܐ ܕܥܠܬܘܢ ܠܐܪܥܐ ܘܢܨܒܬܘܢ ܟܠ ܐܝ̈ܠܢܐ ܕܡܐܟܘܠܬܐ. ܫܒܘܩܘ ܐܢܘܢ ܬܠܬ ܫ̈ܢܝܢ. ܘܠܐ ܬܐܟܠܘܢ ܡܢ ܦܐܖ̈ܝܗܘܢ.24 ܘܒܫܢܬܐ ܕܐܖ̈ܒܥ. ܢܗܘܘܢ ܟܠܗܘܢ ܦܐܖ̈ܝܗܘܢ ܩܘܕܫܐ. ܘܫܘܒܚܐ ܠܡܪܝܐ.25 ܘܒܫܢܬܐ ܕܚܡܫ ܐܟܘܠܘ ܦܐܖ̈ܝܗܘܢ. ܘܢܘܣܦܘܢ ܠܟܘܢ ܥ̈ܠܠܬܗܘܢ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ ܐܠܗܟܘܢ.26 ܠܐ ܬܐܟܠܘܢ ܕܡܐ. ܠܐ ܬܢܚܫܘܢ ܒܚܝܘܬ ܟܢܦܐ. ܠܐ ܬܩܨܡܘܢ. 27 ܠܐ ܬܪܒܘܢ ܣܥܪܐ ܕܖ̈ܝܫܝܟܘܢ. ܘܠܐ ܬܚܒܠܘܢ ܦܐܬܐ ܕܕܩ̈ܢܝܟܘܢ28 ܘܚܘܖ̈ܛܬܐ ܥܠ ܢܦܫܐ ܠܐ ܬܥܒܕܘܢ ܒܒܣܪܟܘܢ. ܘܟܬ̈ܒܐ ܕܢܘܩ̈ܕܬܐ ܠܐ ܬܥܒܕܘܢ ܒܟܘܢ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ.29 ܠܐ ܬܦܣ ܠܒܪܬܟ ܕܬܙܢܐ. ܕܠܐ ܬܙܢܐ ܐܪܥܐ ܘܬܬܡܠܐ ܐܪܥܐ ܚܛܝܬܐ. 30 ܐܠܐ ܛܪܘ ܦܘܩ̈ܕܢܝ ܘܡܢ ܡܩܕܫܝ ܕܚܠܘ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ.31 ܠܐ ܬܐܙܠܘܢ ܒܬܪ ܙܟܘܖ̈ܐ ܘܝܕܘ̈ܥܐ. ܘܠܐ ܬܫܐܠܘܢ ܐܢܘܢ. ܕܠܐ ܬܬܛܡܐܘܢ ܒܗܘܢ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ ܐܠܗܟܘܢ.32 ܡܢ ܩܕܡ ܣܒܐ ܗܘܝܬ ܩ̇ܐܡ. ܘܗܘܝܬ ܡܝܩܪ ܠܡ̇ܢ ܕܩܫܝܫ ܡܢܟ. ܘܕܚܠ ܡܢ ܐܠܗܟ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ܀33 ܘܟܕ ܢܥܡܪ ܥܡܟܘܢ ܐܝܢܐ ܕܡܬܦܢܐ ܠܘܬܝ. ܠܐ ܬܥܠܒܘܢܗ34 ܐܠܐ ܐܟܘܬܟܘܢ ܘܡܢܟܘܢ ܢܗܘܐ. ܘܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܡܬܦܢܝܢ ܠܘܬܝ ܕܥ̇ܡܪܝܢ †ܥܡܟܘܢ†. ܪܚܡܘ ܐܢܘܢ ܐܝܟ ܢܦܫܟܘܢ. ܡܛܠ ܕܐܦ ܐܢܬܘܢ ܥܡܘܖ̈ܐ ܗܘܝܬܘܢ ܒܐܪܥܐ ܕܡܨܪܝܢ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ ܐܠܗܟܘܢ.35 ܠܐ ܬܥܒܕܘܢ ܥܘܠܐ ܒܕܝܢܐ. ܒܡܐܣܬܐ ܘܒܡܬܩܠܐ ܘܒܟܝܠܬܐ. 36 ܡܣܐܬܐ ܕܩܘܫܬܐ ܘܡܬܩܠܐ ܕܩܘܫܬܐ ܘܟܝܠܬܐ ܕܩܘܫܬܐ ܘܗܡܝܢܐ ܕܩܘܫܬܐ ܢܗܘܘܢ ܠܟܘܢ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ ܐܠܗܟܘܢ. ܕܐܦܩܬܟܘܢ ܡܢ ܐܪܥܐ ܕܡܨܪܝܢ.37 ܛܪܘ ܟܠܗܘܢ ܦܘܩ̈ܕܢܝ ܘܟܠܗܘܢ ܕܝܢ̈ܝ ܘܥܒܕܘ ܐܢܘܢ. ܐܢܐ ܐܢܐ ܡܪܝܐ.
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="deu">
        <p>1 Der Herr redete zu Mose und sprach:2 Rede zur ganzen Gemeinde der Kinder Israels und sag zu ihnen: Seid heilig, denn ich bin heilig. Ich bin der Herr, euer Gott.3 Jeder [von euch] soll seinen Vater und seine Mutter fürchten. Ihr sollt meine Gebote halten, denn ich bin der Herr, euer Gott.4 Ihr sollt euch nicht Dämonen zuwenden oder euch gegossene Götter aus Metall machen. Ich bin der Herr, euer Gott.5 Wenn ihr für den Herrn Friedensopfer schlachtet, opfert diejenigen, die wohlgefällig sind.6 Und sie sollen an dem Tag, an dem sie geopfert werden, gegessen werden, oder am folgenden Tag sollen sie gegessen werden. Was aber davon am dritten Tag noch übrig ist, soll im Feuer verbrannt werden und nicht gegessen werden.7 Wenn aber dennoch am dritten Tag davon gegessen wird, ist es ein Greuel. Es wird nicht angenommen werden.8 Und wer davon isst, wird für seine Sünde bestraft werden, denn er hat die Heiligkeit des Herrn entweiht. Du sollst einen solchen Menschen aus seinem Volk ausrotten. 9 Wenn ihr die Ernte eures Landes einbringt, sollt ihr die Ränder eures Feldes nicht vollständig abernten und keine Nachlese von eurer Ernte einsammeln.10 Ihr sollt eure Weinberge nicht nachlesen und die abgefallenen Früchte eurer Olivenbäume nicht einsammeln, sondern ihr sollt sie den Armen und denjenigen, die sich an mich wenden, überlassen, denn ich bin der Herr, euer Gott.11 Ihr sollt nicht stehlen. Ihr sollt nicht lügen. Ihr sollt einander nicht betrügen.12 Ihr sollt nicht falsch bei meinem Namen schwören. Ihr sollt den Namen ihres Gottes nicht entweihen. Ich bin der Herr.13 Du sollst deinen Nächsten weder bedrücken noch unterdrücken. Der Lohn des Tagelöhners soll nicht über Nacht bis zum Morgen bei dir bleiben.14 Du sollst einen Tauben nicht verleumden und vor einem Blinden kein Hindernis aufstellen, sondern du sollst deinen Gott fürchten. Ich bin der Herr.15 Ihr sollt in der Rechtsprechung kein Unrecht tun. Du sollst weder für einen Armen noch für einen Großen Partei nehmen; sondern du sollst deinen Nächsten gerecht richten.16 Du sollst dein Volk nicht verleumden und nicht auftreten gegen das Blut deines Nächsten [d.h. durch Verleumdungen seine Hinrichtung bewirken]! Ich bin der Herr.
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
        <p>1 The Lord spoke to Moses and said to him:2 Speak to the whole assembly of the children of Israel and say to them: Be holy because I am holy. I am the Lord your God.3 Each (of you), fear your father and your mother. Keep my commandments because I am the Lord your God.4 You shall not devote yourselves to demons or make for yourselves gods of molten metal. I am the Lord your God.5 Whenever you offer sacrifices of well-being to the Lord, sacrifice ones that are acceptable.6 And on the day that they are sacrificed, they should be eaten, or they should be eaten by the next day. But anything that remains by the third day must be burned in a fire and not eaten.7 If it is eaten at all on the third day, it is (considered) a despicable act. It will not be tolerated.8 And whoever eats from it will bear sin because of the one who profanes the Lord’s holy (portion). You must cut off such a person from his people.9 Whenever you reap your land’s harvest, you shall not completely harvest the borders of your fields, nor shall you collect the gleanings of your harvest.10 You shall not pick your vineyards (bare), nor shall you collect the fallen fruit of your olive trees. Instead, leave them for the poor and for those who turn to me. For I am the Lord your God.11 You shall not steal. You shall not cheat. You shall not deal deceptively with one another.12 You shall not swear falsely by my name. You shall not profane the name of your God. I am the Lord.13 You shall not oppress your neighbor, nor shall you coerce him with force. The payment of a hireling must not remain with you through the night until morning.14 You shall not slander the deaf or set up a stumbling block in front of the blind. But fear your God; I am the Lord.15 You shall not render a wicked ruling: you shall not favor the poor, and surely not (favor) the powerful. Instead, judge your neighbor justly.16 You shall not slander your people, nor make (a legal) pronouncement on the blood (money) of your neighbor. For I am the Lord.17 You shall not hate your brother in your heart. You indeed must admonish your neighbor, but you must not incur guilt because of him.18 You shall not look on the sons of your people with enmity, but love your neighbor as yourself. I am the Lord.19 Keep my commandments! You shall not allow your animal(s) to mate by mixing (species). You shall not sow your fields with mixed (seed). Nor shall you wear fabrics that are made of a mixture of blended materials.20 (As for) a man who sleeps with a woman, sexually, and she is his maidservant bought by (another) man, but she has not been (legally) redeemed nor (her) freedom granted to her, inquiries will be brought against them. They shall not be killed since she is not a free woman.21 He must bring his offering to the Lord, to the entrance of the Tent of Time – a ram for a sin offering.22 Then the priest shall perform atonement on his behalf with the ram of the sin offering before the Lord on account of the sin, which he committed. Then the sin, which he committed, will be forgiven him.23 When you have entered the land and have planted any trees for food, leave them alone for three years. You shall not eat their fruit.24 On the fourth year, all of their fruit shall be a holy (portion) and a glorification of the Lord.25 On the fifth year, eat their fruit, and their produce will be plentiful for you. I am the Lord your God.26 You shall not eat blood. You shall not practice augury nor divination.27 You shall not let the hair on your head grow long. Nor shall you trim the edge of your beard.28 You shall not make incisions in your flesh for a person. Nor shall you make tattoo marks on yourselves. I am the Lord.29 You shall not allow your daughter to be a prostitute lest the land become a prostitute and the land become full of sin.30 But keep my commandments and fear my sanctuary. I am the Lord.31 You shall not follow after or inquire of necromancers or occultists lest you become unclean by them. I am the Lord your God.32 You should rise in the presence of an elder and should honor whoever is older than you. Fear your God. I am the Lord your God.33 When one who turns to me dwells with you, you shall not oppress him.34 Instead, he shall be equal to you and (counted) among you. Love them as yourselves, those who turn to me who settle among. For you too were settlers in the land of Egypt. I am the Lord your God.35 You shall not render a wicked ruling concerning scales, weights, or measures.36 You shall have an honest scale, honest weights, honest measures, and honest capacity measures. I am the Lord your God who brought you out of the land of Egypt.37 Keep all of my commandments and all of my rulings. Observe them! I am the Lord.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
