<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tuk_doi">
  <!--add the DOI here!-->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Leben des Heiligen Clemens (syrisch)</title>
        <title/>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <date calendar="#Gregorian">19-12-2024</date>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
        <idno type="tuk_DOI">askxxx</idno>
        <!--the DOI could be repeated here-->
        <idno type="instID">askxxx</idno>
        <!--CCint.institutional ID-->
        <idno type="CCTUKID"/>
        <!--CCint.msID-->
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:id="tuk_733" xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>Corpus Coranicum</repository>
            <idno>733</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>F. de Blois 2002: p. 23 bemerkt bezüglich des koranischen Begriffes ḥanīf, dass auch im Koran in 16:120 eine ursprüngliche Bedeutung 'Heide' vorliegen kann. Er verweist auf die syrische Vita Sancti Clementis, welche die Stellung Abrahams folgendermaßen beschreibt: Und es erfüllte sich das Wort der Schrift in ihnen, welches sagt: "Wer Gott fürchtet, handelt gerecht", und "Abraham glaubte an Gott, als er (noch) ein Heide war (bzw. als Heide) und Er gab ihm den Lohn für seine Gerechtigkeit".
	Zu vergleichen ist damit Q 16:120 ʾinnā Ibrahīma kāna ʾummatan qānitan li-llāhi ḥanīfan wa lam yakun mina l-mušrikīn. "Abraham war eine gottgehorsame Nation, als Heide (ḥanīfan), und kein Beigeseller."
	Abraham würde also in beiden Fällen als 'rechtgläubiger Heide' charakterisiert. Davon ausgehend, entwickelt sich im koranischen Kontext die Bedeutung von ḥanīf als nicht-jüdischem bzw. nicht-christlichem Rechtgläubigen.
	Die Bezeichnung Abrahams als 'Nation', arabisch ʾumma, ist so zu verstehen, dass damit Abraham und seine Sippe/ Nachkommenschaft gemeint ist. Vgl. dazu Genesis 18:18: wə-ʾAbrāhām hāyô yihye lə-gôy gādôl wə-ʿāṣûm wə-nibrəkû bô kol gôyay hā-ʾāreṣ 'Abraham soll doch zu einem großen, mächtigen Volk werden, durch ihn sollen alle Völker der Erde Segen erlangen.' Bereits Karl Ahrens verweist, mit Hinweis auf Römer 4:11f., im Übrigen auf die christliche Vorstellung Abrahams als "Vater der gläubig werdenden Heiden" und sieht darin einen Ursprung der koranischen Vorstellung des Hanifentums; d.h. Abraham sei 'Heide' aber eben kein Götzendiener gewesen (Ahrens 1930: p. 190).

	Zu ḥanīf, vgl. Jeffery 1938: p. 112-115.
</summary>
            <msItem>
              <title>Leben des Heiligen Clemens (syrisch)</title>
              <author/>
              <textLang mainLang="syc">Syrisch</textLang>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc> </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate calendar="gregorian">225-245?</origDate>
              <origPlace>Nord-Ost Syrien?</origPlace>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <source>
                  <p>The editors and contributions to Corpus Coranicum.</p>
                </source>
              </recordHist>
            </adminInfo>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl type="edition">Alphonse Mingana, Some Early Judaeo-Christian Documents in the John Rylands Library, Manchester 1917, S. 34-36.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Ahrens, Karl: &amp;#x201E;Christliches im Qoran. Eine Nachlese&amp;#x201C;. In: Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morgenl&amp;#xE4;ndischen Gesellschaft 84 (1930), S. 15&amp;#x2013;68, 148&amp;#x2013;190.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Blois, Fran&amp;#xE7;ois de: &amp;#x201E;Na&amp;#x1E63;r&amp;#x101;n&amp;#x12B; (&amp;#x39D;&amp;#x3B1;&amp;#x3B6;&amp;#x3C9;&amp;#x3C1;&amp;#x3B1;&amp;#x20B;&amp;#x3BF;&amp;#x3C2;) and &amp;#x1E25;an&amp;#x12B;f (&amp;#x1F10;&amp;#x3B8;&amp;#x3BD;&amp;#x3B9;&amp;#x3BA;&amp;#x3CC;&amp;#x3C2;): Studies on the Religious Vocabulary of Christianity and of Islam&amp;#x201C;. In: Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies 65 (2002), S. 1&amp;#x2013;30.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Jeffery, Arthur: The foreign vocabulary of the Qur&amp;#x2019;&amp;#x101;n. Oriental Institute, Baroda 1938.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Created as part of
            <name type="project">Corpus Coranicum Project</name>
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantsreader">
          <bibl>Variants Readers</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantssource">
          <bibl>Variants Sources</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="tuk.cat">
          <bibl>TUK Categories</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="geoname">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="https://www.geonames.org/">Geonames</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="local">
          <bibl>'Sigle' is a unique id assigned by Michael Marx to a specific reader in the reading
                variants.
            </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change type="TEI_record_creater">
        <persName role="dtc">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
      </change>
      <change type="transliteration">
        <persName key="" role="trc">David Kiltz</persName>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription" xml:lang="syc">
        <p>ܬܘܒ ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܕܥܠ ܩܠܝܡܝܣ ܬܠܡܝܕܗ ܕܫܡܥܘܢ ܟܐܦܐ ܘܥܠ ܐܒܗܘ̈ܗܝ ܘܐܚܘ̈ܗܝ ܕܐܝܟܢ ܐܦ ܗܢܘܢ ܐܬܬܠܡܕܘܓܒܪܐ ܚܕ ܥܬܝܪܐ ܐܝܬ ܗܘܐ ܒܪܘܡܝ ܡܕܝܢܬܐ ܘܫܡܗ ܦܘܣܛܝܢܝܐܢܘܣ ܘܫܡܐ ܕܐܢܬܬܐ ܕܝܠܗ ܡܝܛܪܘܕܘܪܐ ܘܠܦܬܟܖ̈ܐ ܣܓܕܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܓܠܝܐܝܬ ܘܟܕ ܠܐ ܝܕܥܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܠܐܠܗܐ ܫܪܝܪܐܝܬ ܘܟܐܢܐܝܬ ܠܗ ܦܠܝܚܢ ܗܘܘ ܘܙܕܩ̈ܬܐ ܡ̣ܢ ܡܖ̈ܗܛܝܗܘܢ ܠܡܣܟܢ̈ܐ ܝܗܒܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܐܝܟ ܐܝܘܒ ܘܠܐܟܣ̈ܢܝܐ ܘܠܡܣܟܢ̈ܐ ܡܩܒܠܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܐܝܟ ܐܒܪܗܡ ܘܫܠܡܬ݀ ܥܠܝܗܘܢ ܡܠܬ ܟܬܒܐ ܕܐܡܪ ܕܕܚܠ ܠܐܠܗܐ ܟܐܢܐܝܬ ܡܬܕܒܪ ܘܗܝ̇ ܕܗܝܡܢ ܐܒܪܗܡ ܠܐܠܗܐ ܟܕ ܚܢܦܐ ܗܘܐ ܘܝܗܒ ܠܗ ܐܓܪܐ ܕܟܐܢܘܬܗ ܘܗܢܐ ܟܐܢܐ ܦܘܣܛܝܢܝܐܢܘܣ ܒܚܪܬܐ ܕܫܢܘ̈ܗܝ ܩܒܠ ܐܓܪܐ ܕܟܐܢܘܬܗ ܘܐܝܟ ܕܐܬܢܣܝܘ ܐܒܪܗܡ ܘܣܪܐ ܒܝܕ ܐܝܣܚܩ ܗܟܢ ܐܦ ܗܢܘܢ ܓܠܝܙܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܡ̣ܢ ܝܪܬܐ ܐܝܟ ܕܬܫܬܡܫ ܒܗܘܢ ܟܐܢܘܬܐ ܘܬܣܓܐ ܒܗܘܢ ܙܕܝܩܘܬܐ.ܐܠܐ ܦܠ̇ܚ ܐܓܝܪܐ ܠܐ ܡܫܟܚ ܬܒ̇ܥ ܐܓܪܗ ܥܕܡܐ ܕܦܠܚܘ ܟܐܢ̈ܐ ܠܐ ܟܬܝܒ ܕܢܣܒܘ ܦܘܪܥܢܐ ܘܥܕܡܐ ܕܚܛܘ ܒܝܫ̈ܐ ܠܐ ܩܒܠܘ ܠܓܙܪ ܕܝܢܐ. ܐܠܘܠܐ ܐܣܟܠ ܬܕܡ ܠܐ ܐܦܩܘܗܝ ܡ̣ܢ ܦܪܕܝܣܐ ܘܐܠܘܠܐ ܕܩܛ̣ܠ ܩܐܝܢ ܠܐ ܫ̣ܪܐ ܙܘܥܐ ܒܗܕܡܘ̈ܗܝ ܥܕܡܐ ܕܐܘܕܝ ܓܝܣܐ ܠܐ ܥܠ̣ ܗܘܐ ܠܓܘ ܦܪܕܝܣܐ. ܘܗܟܢܐ ܗܠܝܢ ܟܐܢ̈ܐ ܦܘܣܛܝܢܝܐܢܘܣ ܘܒܪܬ ܙܘܓܗ ܐܝܟ ܥܡ̈ܠܝܗܘܢ ܦܘܖ̈ܥܢܝܗܘܢ. ܘܐܝܟ ܕܐܡܪܬ ܥܠ ܖ̈ܗܛܝܗܘܢ ܐܡܪ ܗܫܐ ܥܠ ܢܨܚܢܝ̈ܗܘܢ. ܡ̇ܢ ܕܐܝܬ ܠܗ ܬܕܢ̈ܐ ܫܦ̈ܝܬܐ ܕܡܠܝ̈ ܚܘܒܐ ܢܩܪܘܒ ܢܫܡܥ ܫܪܒܐ ܪܚܝܡܐ ܘܒܗ ܢܬܒܣܡ. ܡܓܙܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܡ̣ܢ ܝܠܕܐ ܗܢܘܢ ܟܐܢ̈ܐ ܘܐܒܝܠܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܡ̣ܢ ܢܘܓܪܐ ܘܒܬܪ ܙܒܢܐ ܨܒܐ ܐܠܗܐ ܕܢܒܝܐ ܐܢܘܢ ܘܢܚܘܐ ܐܢܘܢ ܕܠܐ ܛܠ̣ܡ ܐܓܪܗܘܢ. ܘܒܚܕܐ ܟܪܣܐ ܥܕܬ݀ ܡܝܛܪܘܕܘܪܐ ܬܪܝܢ ܥܘܠ̈ܐ ܐܝܟ ܪܦܩܐ ܠܥܝܣܘ ܘܠܝܥܩܘܒ. ܘܩܪܬ݀ ܐܢܘܢ ܫܡܗ̈ܐ ܠܪܒܐ ܦܘܣܛܝܢܘܣ ܘܠܙܥܘܪܐ ܦܘܣܛܘܣ. ܘܬܘܒ ܝܠܕܬ݀ ܝܠܕܐ ܐܚܪܢܐ ܘܩܪܬܗ ܩܠܝܡܝܣ.ܗܝܕܝܢ ܒܝܫܐ ܘܒܥܠܕܒܒܐ ܕܟܐܢܘܬܐ ܨܒܐ ܕܢܥܪܩܠ ܐܢܘܢ ܒܨܢܥܬܗ ܘܢܥܘܠ ܨܝܕ ܫܦܝܖ̈ܐ. ܐܫܬܘܕܝ ܡܪܝܐ ܦܪܕܝܣܐ ܕܥܕܢ ܠܚܘܬ ܘܐܕܡ ܘܐܚܬ ܐܢܘܢ ܒܝܫܐ ܡ̣ܢ ܕܖ̈ܓܝܗܘܢ ܘܫܕܪ ܐܠܗܐ ܠܝܚܝܕܝܗ ܘܦܪܩ ܐܢܘܢ ܘܐܣܩ ܐܢܘܢ ܠܐܬܪܐ ܕܡܥܠܝ ܡ̣ܢ ܩܕܡܝܐ. ܘܡܠܟ ܒܝܫܐ ܠܐܚܘ̈ܗܝ ܕܝܘܣܦ ܕܢܙܒܢܘܢܝܗܝ ܘܐܠܗܐ ܥܒܕܗ ܠܗܘܢ ܦܪܘܩܐ ܒܝܘܡܐ ܕܐܘܠܨܢܐ. ܘܠܡܝܛܪܘܕܘܪܐ ܒܓܘܪܐ ܣܢܝܐ ܨܒܐ ܕܢܚܒܠ ܘܗܕܐ ܥܠܬܐ ܩܪܬܗ̇ ܘܦܢܬ݀ ܨܝܕ ܐܠܗܐ. ܠܦܘܣܛܝܢܝܐܢܘܣ ܐܚܐ ܐܝܬ ܗܘܐ ܘܡܠܟܗ ܒܝܫܐ ܘܐܬܪܓܪܓ ܠܐܢܬܬܐ ܕܐܚܘܗܝ ܘܟܕ ܙܒ̈ܢܬܐ ܣܓܝ̈ܐܬܐ ܐܠ̇ܨ ܗܘܐ ܠܗ̇ ܗܝ ܡܗܝܡܢܬܐ ܠܐ ܐܬܦܠܓܬ݀ ܥܠ ܫܘܬܦܗ̇ ܘܐܬܚܫܒܬ݀ ܕܐܝܟܢܐ ܬܙܟܐ ܠܒܝܫܐ ܘܪܟܒܬ݀ ܥܠܬܐ ܐܝܟ ܗܘ̇ ܕܚܠܡܐ ܚܙܬ݀ ܕܬܣܒ ܠܒ̈ܢܝܗ̇ ܘܬܪܚܩ ܡ̣ܢ ܨܝܕ ܒܥܠܗ̇ ܕܕܠܡܐ ܟܒܪ ܟܕ ܡܬܪܚܩܐ ܕܥ̇ܟܐ ܢܘܪܐ ܕܟܪܝܟܐ ܠܗ ܠܗܘ̇ ܡܪܚܐ. 
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="deu">
        <p>
	Und es erfüllte sich das Wort der Schrift in ihnen, welches sagt: "Wer Gott fürchtet, handelt gerecht", und "Abraham glaubte an Gott, als er (noch) ein Heide war und er gab ihm den Lohn für seine Gerechtigkeit".
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
        <p>Again a story about Clement, the disciple of Simon Cephas, and about his parents and his brothers, how they also have been evangelized.There was in the city of Rome a rich man called Faustinianus, and the name of his wife was Mitrodora. They openly worshipped idols, and though they did not know God, they served Him truly and justly. They gave alms to the poor from their riches, like Job, and received the strangers and the poor like Abraham. The word of the Scripture was fulfilled in them, which says: “He who fears God behaves justly,” and “Abraham believed in God, when still pagan, and He gave him the reward of his justice”. And this just Faustinianus received the reward of his justice at the end of his life. And as Abraham and Sarah have been tested through Isaac, so (Faustinianus and Mitrodora) were without an heir, in order that justice might be performed in them, and righteousness might increase through them.If the hired man does not work, he cannot claim his salary, because it is not written that just people received any reward except after they had worked, and wicked people any chastisement till they had sinned. If Adam had not transgressed, he would not have been driven out of Paradise; and if Cain had not committed murder, trepidation would not have dwelt in his limbs; and the robber did not enter into Paradise till he confessed. So is the case with these just people, Faustinianus and his wife, whose rewards are according to their toil; and since I have narrated the nature of their work, I will now relate their exploits. He who has the clean ears of the words of love, let him approach and hear a pleasant account and delight in it.These righteous people were deprived of posterity, and for a long time they were distressed. After a certain time, God wished to comfort them and to show them that He had not kept back their reward from them. Mitrodora, then, had two babes in her womb, as Rebecca had Esau and Jacob. She gave them names, to the elder Faustinus and to the younger Faustus. She brought forth also another child, and she called him Clement.Then the Evil One, the enemy of justice, wished to make them stumble by his craftiness, and to insinuate himself to these good people. The Lord promised to Eve and Adam the paradise of Eden, and the Evil One degraded them from their ranks, and God sent His Only Begotten, and saved them and made them go up to a place higher than the first. The Devil suggested to the brothers of Joseph to sell him, and God made him a redeemer to them, in the day of distress. (The Devil) wished, too, to dishonour Mitrodora by a detestable adultery, and this motive distracted her, and she returned to God.Faustinianus had a brother, and the Evil One insinuated to him to conceive a passion for the wife of his brother; and though he repeatedly solicited her, the faithful (woman) never wronged her husband, and she thought of a means to vanquish the Evil One. She made a false pretence, as if she had dreamt it, to take her boys and to go away from her husband, in order that by her absence the fire surrounding that violent man might be extinguished. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
