<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tuk_doi">
  <!--add the DOI here!-->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Babylonischer Talmud, Baba batra 16a</title>
        <title/>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <date calendar="#Gregorian">19-12-2024</date>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
        <idno type="tuk_DOI">askxxx</idno>
        <!--the DOI could be repeated here-->
        <idno type="instID">askxxx</idno>
        <!--CCint.institutional ID-->
        <idno type="CCTUKID"/>
        <!--CCint.msID-->
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:id="tuk_1098" xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>Corpus Coranicum</repository>
            <idno>1098</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>
	Wie im Koran erscheint auch im babylonischen Talmud der Satan in der Rolle des Verführers der Menschen. Diese Vorstellung, die später im Christentum (vgl. Speyer 1931: p. 59-60) und im Koran begegnet,
 läßt sich zudem bereits im Jubiläenbuch 
nachweisen (vgl. TUK_0919, TUK_0920). In ihr lässt sich das Bemühen erkennen, Gott zu "entlasten", indem schlechte Dinge dem Satan zugeschrieben werden, der wiederum nur in einem ihm von Gott 
zugestandenen Handlungsrahmen agieren kann (Berger 1981: p. 282; vgl. dazu z.B. Hiob 1:6-12 (TUK_0411), wo der Satan Gottes Erlaubnis erhält, Hiob Schaden zuzufügen).
</summary>
            <msItem>
              <title>Babylonischer Talmud, Baba batra 16a</title>
              <author/>
              <textLang mainLang="heb">Hebräisch</textLang>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc> </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate calendar="gregorian">vor 7. Jh. n. Chr. (Endredaktion)</origDate>
              <origPlace>Mesopotamien</origPlace>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <source>
                  <p>The editors and contributions to Corpus Coranicum.</p>
                </source>
              </recordHist>
            </adminInfo>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl type="edition">Wilna 1880-1886</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Berger, Klaus: Das Buch der Jubil&amp;#xE4;en. 1981.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Speyer, Heinrich: Die biblischen Erz&amp;#xE4;hlungen im Qoran. C. Schulze, Gr&amp;#xE4;fenhainichen 1931.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Created as part of
            <name type="project">Corpus Coranicum Project</name>
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantsreader">
          <bibl>Variants Readers</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantssource">
          <bibl>Variants Sources</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="tuk.cat">
          <bibl>TUK Categories</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="geoname">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="https://www.geonames.org/">Geonames</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="local">
          <bibl>'Sigle' is a unique id assigned by Michael Marx to a specific reader in the reading
                variants.
            </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change type="TEI_record_creater">
        <persName role="dtc">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
      </change>
      <change type="transliteration">
        <persName key="" role="trc">Veronika Roth</persName>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription" xml:lang="heb">
        <p>ויהי היום ויבואו בני האלהים להתיצב וגו' ויאמר ה' אל השטן אי מזה תבא ויען השטן את ה' ויאמר משוט בארץ [וגו'] אמר לפניו רבש"ע שטתי בכל העולם ולא מצאתי כעבדך אברהם שאמרת לו קום התהלך בארץ לארכה ולרחבה כי לך אתננה ובשעה שבקש לקבור שרה לא מצא מקום לקוברה ולא הרהר אחר מדותיך ויאמר ה' אל השטן השמת לבך אל עבדי איוב כי אין כמוהו בארץ וגו' ועודנו מחזיק בתומתו ותסיתני בו לבלעו חנם אמר רבי יוחנן אלמלא מקרא כתוב אי אפשר לאומרו כאדם שמסיתין אותו וניסת במתניתא תנא יורד ומתעה ועולה ומרגיז נוטל רשות ונוטל נשמה</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="deu">
        <p>Nun geschah es eines Tages, daß die Gottessöhne kamen, sich vor den Herrn zu stellen etc. Da fragte der Herr den Satan: Woher kommst du? Der Satan antwortete dem Herrn und sprach: Von einem Streifzug auf der Erde (Hiob 2:1-2). Er sprach vor ihm: Herr der Welt, ich bin in der ganzen Welt umhergestreift und fand keinen, der so treu wäre, wie dein Knecht Abraham. Du sagtest zu ihm: mache dich auf und durchziehe das Land nach seiner Länge und Breite, denn dir will ich es geben (Gen 13:17), dennoch trug er deiner Handlungsweise nichts nach, als er keine Stätte fand, seine Frau Sara zu begraben. Da sprach der Herr zum Satan: hast du acht gehabt auf meinen Knecht Ijob, denn seinesgleichen gibt es niemand auf Erden etc. Noch hält er fest an seiner Frömmigkeit, und du hast mich verleitet, ihn ohne Grund zu verderben (Hiob 2:3). R. Joḥanan sagte, wenn dies kein geschriebener Schriftvers wäre, dürfte man es nicht sagen; gleich einem Menschen, den man verleitet und er sich verleiten läßt.
	In einer Barajtha wird gelehrt: Er steigt hinab und verführt, steigt hinauf und klagt an, holt sich Vollmacht und nimmt die Seele.
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
        <p>Again there was a day when the sons of God came to present themselves ... and the Lord said unto Satan, From whence comest thou? And Satan answered the Lord and said, From going to and fro in the earth, etc(Job 2:1-2). He said: Sovereign of the Universe, I have traversed the whole earth, and have not found one like thy servant Abraham. For thou didst say to him, Arise, walk through the land in the length of it and the breadth of it, for to thee I will give it (Gen 13:17), and when he wanted to bury Sarah he could not find a place in which to bury her, and yet he did not complain against thy ways. Then the Lord said unto Satan, Hast thou considered my servant Job, for there is none like him in the earth ... and he still holdeth fast his integrity, although thou movedst me against him to destroy him without cause (Job 2:3). Said R. Johanan: Were it not expressly stated in the Scripture, we would not dare to say it. [God is made to appear] like a man who allows himself to be persuaded against his better judgment. A Tanna taught: [Satan] comes down to earth and seduces, then ascends to heaven and awakens wrath; permission is granted to him and he takes away the soul.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
