<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/corpus_coranicum.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tuk_doi">
  <!--add the DOI here!-->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>De opificio mundi 1:131-133</title>
        <title/>
        <funder>Corpus Coranicum (BBAW)</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <persName key="person_39907760" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/39907760" role="edt">Michael Marx</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Tobias J. Jocham</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
          <persName role="ctb">Huw Jones</persName>
          <resp>Edited by Michael Marx in collaboration with Tobias J. Jocham
        et. al. TEI version created by Yasmin Faghihi
        and Huw Jones
    </resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Corpus Coranicum</publisher>
        <date calendar="#Gregorian">19-12-2024</date>
        <pubPlace>
          <address>
            <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            <street>Jägerstraße 22/23</street>
            <postCode>10117</postCode>
            <addrLine>
              <ref target="https://corpuscoranicum.de/">Corpus Coranicum</ref>
            </addrLine>
            <addrLine>
              <email>corpuscoranicum@bbaw.de</email>
            </addrLine>
            <settlement type="city">Berlin</settlement>
            <country key="de">Germany</country>
          </address>
        </pubPlace>
        <idno type="tuk_DOI">askxxx</idno>
        <!--the DOI could be repeated here-->
        <idno type="instID">askxxx</idno>
        <!--CCint.institutional ID-->
        <idno type="CCTUKID"/>
        <!--CCint.msID-->
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:id="tuk_1118" xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>Corpus Coranicum</repository>
            <idno>1118</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>Die genannten Koranstellen weisen im Rahmen von ʾayāt-Serien (vgl. dazu den Kommentar zu Q 88:17-20 sowie Neuwirth 2010: p. 433-450) darauf hin, dass Gott süßes und salziges Wasser erschaffen hat, bzw. die beiden Wasser getrennt hat. Auch Philo von Alexandria, der versucht, die biblische Schöpfungserzählung mit griechischer Philosophie in Einklang zu bringen (vgl. dazu Miletto 2009), unterscheidet in seiner Auslegung von Genesis 2:6 ("aber Feuchtigkeit stieg aus der Erde auf und tränkte die ganze Fläche des Ackerbodens") zwischen süßem und salzigem Wasser. Auch im Babylonischen Talmud wird zwischen süßem und salzigem Wasser unterschieden (TUK_1119). Zu weiteren Belegstellen vgl. Speyer 1931: p. 9-10 und Wensinck 1918. All diesen Texten liegt eine im alten Orient und der Spätantike weitverbreitete kosmologische Vorstellung zugrunde. Dieser zufolge
 ist die Erde von Wasser umgeben, wobei die beiden Elemente bei der 
Schöpfung getrennt wurden und eine Barriere zwischen sie gesetzt wurde (vgl. z.B. Ps 
104:5-9, TUK_0557) (Neuwirth 2001: p. 443) (Wensinck 1918: p. 2, 21-24). Das Wasser ist wiederum in zwei Ozeane, einer süß und einer salzig, 
geteilt, die ebenfalls durch eine Schranke (im Koran barzaḫ, bzw. ḥāǧiz genannt) getrennt werden (Neuwirth 2001: p. 443, 445). In der hebräischen und syrischen Literatur lässt sich zudem eine Dreiteilung des Ozeans feststellen: Ein Teil davon befindet sich unter der Erde, ein Teil auf der Erde und einer über dem Himmel. Dabei gilt das unterirdische Süßwassermeer als der Ursprung der Quellen und Flüsse, das himmlische als Ursprung des Regens. Der die Erde umgebende Ozean ist dagegen salzig (Wensinck 1918: p. 17-21, 36-37).In den genannten Koranstellen bezieht sich baḥrān ("die beiden Meere") auf das Wasser über- und unterhalb des Firmaments (vgl. Gen 
1:6-8). Ephrem erklärt in seinem Genesis-Kommentar, dass das obere Wasser süß 
blieb und das untere salzig wurde. Der himmlische Ozean fungiert im Koran als eine Art 
Zisterne, aus der der Regen kommt. Er bildet die Grundlage allen Süßwassers, auch der 
Flüsse. maǧmaʿ al-baḥrain (Q 18:60) bezeichnet den Ort, an dem sich der 
himmlische und der irdische Ozean treffen (Tesei 2015: p. 28-29).Zu den entsprechenden babylonischen Vorstellungen vgl. Lambert 2013: p. 171, 197-199, 217-218, 236-238, 396-398, 445-447, 459-461 und Horowitz 1998: p. 105, 131-132, 334-347.</summary>
            <msItem>
              <title>De opificio mundi 1:131-133</title>
              <author>Philo von Alexandria (ca. 20/10 v. Chr. - 40/50 n.Chr.)</author>
              <textLang mainLang="ell">Griechisch</textLang>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc> </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate calendar="gregorian">vor 50 n. Chr.</origDate>
              <origPlace>Alexandria</origPlace>
            </origin>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <source>
                  <p>The editors and contributions to Corpus Coranicum.</p>
                </source>
              </recordHist>
            </adminInfo>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl type="edition">Philonis Alexandrini Opera quae supersunt ediderunt Leopoldus Cohn et Paulus Wendland Vol. I, p. 6-60 Berolini 1896.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Horowitz, Wayne: Mesopotamian Cosmic Geography. Eisenbrauns, Winona Lake 1998.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Lambert, W.G.: Babylonian Creation Myths. Eisenbrauns, Winona Lake 2013.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Miletto, Gianfranco: &amp;#x201E;Philo von Alexandrien&amp;#x201C; (M. Bauks, K. Koenen, &amp;amp; S. Alkier, Hrsg.). Wissenschaftliches Bibellexikon.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Neuwirth, Angelika: &amp;#x201E;Cosmology&amp;#x201C;. Encyclopaedia of the Qur&amp;#x2019;&amp;#x101;n 1: 440&amp;#x2013;457.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Neuwirth, Angelika: Der Koran als Text der Sp&amp;#xE4;tantike: ein europ&amp;#xE4;ischer Zugang. Verl. der Weltreligionen, Berlin 2010.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Speyer, Heinrich: Die biblischen Erz&amp;#xE4;hlungen im Qoran. C. Schulze, Gr&amp;#xE4;fenhainichen 1931.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Tesei, Tommaso: &amp;#x201E;Some Cosmological Notions from Late Antiquity in Q 18:60-65: The Quran in Light of Its Cultural Context&amp;#x201C;. In: Journal of the American Oriental Society 135.1 (2015), S. 19&amp;#x2013;31.</bibl>
              <bibl type="literatur">Wensinck, A.J.: The Ocean in the Literature of the Western Semites. Johannes M&amp;#xFC;ller, Amsterdam 1918.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Created as part of
            <name type="project">Corpus Coranicum Project</name>
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantsreader">
          <bibl>Variants Readers</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="variantssource">
          <bibl>Variants Sources</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="tuk.cat">
          <bibl>TUK Categories</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="geoname">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="https://www.geonames.org/">Geonames</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="local">
          <bibl>'Sigle' is a unique id assigned by Michael Marx to a specific reader in the reading
                variants.
            </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change type="TEI_record_creater">
        <persName role="dtc">Yasmin Faghihi</persName>
      </change>
      <change type="transliteration">
        <persName key="" role="trc">Veronika Roth</persName>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription" xml:lang="ell">
        <p>
	131 τῆς δ᾽ ἀκολουθίας ἐχόμενος καὶ τὸν εἱρμὸν τῶν ἑπομένων πρὸς τὰ ἡγούμενα διατρηρῶν ἑξῆς λέγει· "πηγὴ δ᾽ ἀνέβαινεν ἐκ τῆς γῆς καὶ ἐπότιζε πᾶν τὸ πρόσωπον τῆς γῆσ" (Gen 2:6). οἱ μὲν ἄλλοι φιλόσοφοι τὸ σύμπαν ὕδωρ ἓν στοιχεῖον εἶναί φασιλέγω τῶν τεττάρων, ἐξ ὧν ὁ κόσμος ἐδημιουργήθη. Μωυσῆς δ᾽ ὀξυωπεστέροις ὄμμασι καὶ τὰ μακρὰν εἰωθὼς εὖ μάλα θεωρεῖν καὶ καταλαμβάνειν στοιχεῖον μὲν οἴεται εἶναι τὴν μεγάλην θάλατταν, μοῖραν τετάρτην τῶν συμπάντων, ἣν οἱ μετ᾽ αὐτὸν Ὠκεανὸν προσαγορεύοντες τὰ παρ᾽ ἡμῖν πλωτὰ πελάγη λιμένων ἔχειν μεγέθη νομίζουσι, τὸ δὲ γλυκὺ καὶ πότιμον ὕδωρ διέκρινεν ἀπὸ τοῦ θαλαττίου προσκατατάξας αὐτὸ τῇ γῇ καὶ μέρος ταύτης ὑπολαβών, οὐκ ἐκείνου, διὰ τὴν λεχθεῖσαν αἰτίαν πρότερον, ἵν᾽ ὡς ἂν ὑπὸ δεσμοῦ συνέχηται γλυκείᾳ ποιότητι κόλλης τρόπον ἑνούσης· ξηρὰ γὰρ ἀπολειφθεῖσα, μὴ παραδυομένης νοτίδος διὰ τῶν ἀραιωμάτων πολυσχιδῶς ἐπιφοιτώσης, κἂνκαί διελέλυτο· συνέχεται δὲ καὶ διαμένει τὰ μὲν πνεύματος ἑνωτικοῦ δυνάμει, τὰ δὲ τῆς νοτίδος οὐκ ἐώσης ἀφαυαινομένην κατὰ τρύφη μικρὰ καὶ μεγάλα θρύπτεσθαι. 132 μία μὲν αἰτία ἥδε, λεκτέον δὲ καὶ ἑτέραν στοχαζομένην ὥσπερ σκοποῦ τῆς ἀληθείας· οὐδὲν τῶν γηγενῶν ἄνευ ὑγρᾶς οὐσίας συνίστασθαι πέφυκε· μηνύουσι δ’ αἱ καταβολαὶ τῶν σπερμάτων, ἅπερ ἢ ὑγρά ἐστιν, ὡς τὰ τῶν ζῴων, ἢ οὐκ ἄνευ ὑγρότητος βλαστάνει, τοιαῦτα δὲ τὰ τῶν φυτῶν ἐστιν· ἐξ οὗ δῆλον ὅτι ἀνάγκη τὴν λεχθεῖσαν ὑγρὰν οὐσίαν μέρος εἶναι γῆς τῆς πάντα τικτούσης, καθάπερ ταῖς γυναιξὶ τὴν φορὰν τῶν καταμηνίων· λέγεται γὰρ οὖν καὶ ταῦτα πρὸς ἀνδρῶν φυσικῶν οὐσία σωματικὴ βρεφῶν εἶναι. 133 τῶν δ’ εἰρημένων οὐκ ἀπᾴδει καὶ τὸ μέλλον λέγεσθαι· πάσῃ μητρὶ καθάπερ ἀναγκαιότατον μέρος ἡ φύσις πηγάζοντας ἀνέδωκε μαστοὺς προευτρεπισαμένη τροφὰς τῷ γεννησομένῳ· μήτηρ δ’ ὡς ἔοικε καὶ ἡ γῆ, παρὸ καὶ τοῖς πρώτοις ἔδοξεν αὐτὴν Δήμητραν καλέσαι τὸ μητρὸς καὶ γῆς ὄνομα συνθεῖσιν· οὐ ¦ γὰρ γῆ γυναῖκα, ὡς εἶπε Πλάτων, ἀλλὰ γυνὴ γῆν μεμίμηται, ἣν ἐτύμως τὸ ποιητικὸν γένος παμμήτορα καὶ καρποφόρον καὶ πανδώραν εἴωθεν ὀνομάζειν, ἐπειδὴ πάντων αἰτία γενέσεως καὶ διαμονῆς ζῴων ὁμοῦ καὶ φυτῶν ἐστιν. εἰκότως οὖν καὶ γῇ τῇ πρεσβυτάτῃ καὶ γονιμωτάτῃ μητέρων ἀνέδωκεν ἡ φύσις οἷα μαστοὺς ποταμῶν ῥεῖθρα καὶ πηγῶν, ἵνα καὶ τὰ φυτὰ ἄρδοιτο καὶ ποτὸν ἄφθονον ἔχοι πάντα τὰ ζῷα.
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="deu">
        <p>
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
        <p>
	131 Then, preserving the natural order of things, and having a regard to the connection between what comes afterwards and what has gone before, he says next, "And a fountain went up from the earth and watered the whole face of the earth" (Gen 2:6). For other philosophers affirm that all water is one of the four elements of which the world was composed. But Moses, who was accustomed to contemplate and comprehend matters with a more acute and far-sighted vision, considers thus: the vast sea is an element, being a fourth part of the entire universe, which the men after him denominated the ocean, while they look upon the smaller seas which we sail over in the light of harbors. And he drew a distinction between the sweet and drinkable water and that of the sea, attributing the former to the earth, and considering it a portion of the earth, rather than of the ocean, on account of the reason which I have already mentioned, that is to say, that the earth may be held together by the sweet qualities of the water as by a chain; the water acting in the manner of glue. For if the earth were left entirely dry, so that no moisture arose and penetrated through its holes rising to the surface in various directions, it would split. But now it is held together, and remains lasting, partly by the force of the wind which unites it, and partly because the moisture does not allow it to become dry, and so to be broken up into larger and smaller fragments. 132 This is one reason; and we must also mention another, which is aimed at the truth like an arrow at a mark. It is not the nature of anything upon the earth to exist without a moist essence. And this is indicated by the throwing of seed, which is either moist, as the seed of animals, or else does not shoot up without moisture, such as the seeds of plants; from which it is evident that it follows that the aforesaid moist essence must be a portion of the earth which produces everything, just as the flux of the catamenia is a part of women. For by men who are learned in natural philosophy, this also is said to be the corporeal essence of children. 133 Nor is what we are about to say inconsistent with what has been said; for nature has bestowed upon every mother, as a most indispensable part of her conformation, breasts gushing forth like fountains, having in this manner provided abundant food for the child that is to be born. And the earth also, as it seems, is a mother, from which consideration it occurred to the early ages to call her Demetra, combining the names of mother, and earth. For it is not the earth which imitates the woman, as Plato has said, but the woman who has imitated the earth which the race of poets has been accustomed with truth to call the mother of all things, and the fruit-bearer, and the giver of all things, since she is at the same time the cause of the generation and durability of all things, to the animals and plants. Rightly, therefore, did nature bestow on the earth as the eldest and most fertile of mothers, streams of rivers, and fountains like breasts, in order that the plants might be watered, and that all living things might have abundant supplies of drink. 
</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
